<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>

<document title="SRD 3.5 &gt; Equipment and Gear &gt; Equipment">
<info>
<title>n the marketplace of a big city, armorsmiths and weaponsmiths</title>
<author>AKSmith</author>
<operator>AKSmith</operator>
</info>
<topic level="0" name="Equipment and Gear" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear" docbookid="Equipment0" keywords="equip,gear"><para>This material is Open Game Content, and is licensed for public use under the terms of the Open Game License v1.0a.</para><topic level="1" name="Equipment" origname="Equipment" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment" docbookid="Equipment1" keywords="equip,gear"><para style="heading 1">Equipment</para><para>Assume a character owns at least one outfit of normal clothes. Pick any one of the following clothing outfits: artisan's outfit, entertainer's outfit, explorer's outfit, monk's outfit, peasant's outfit, scholar's outfit, or traveler's outfit.</para><para/><topic level="2" name="Wealth and Money" origname="Wealth and Money" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Wealth_and_Money" docbookid="Equipment2" refname="Wealth and Money" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,monei,wealth"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Wealth and Money" style="heading 2">Wealth and Money</para><topic level="3" name="Coins" origname="Coins" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Wealth_and_Money_Coins" docbookid="Equipment3" refname="Coins" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="coin,equip,gear,monei,wealth"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Coins" style="heading 3">Coins</para><para>The most common coin is the gold piece (gp). A gold piece is worth 10 silver pieces. Each silver piece is worth 10 copper pieces (cp). In addition to copper, silver, and gold coins, there are also platinum pieces (pp), which are each worth 10 gp.</para><para>The standard coin weighs about a third of an ounce (fifty to the pound).</para><para/><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Table: Coins</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell><para><b>----- Exchange Value ----</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell><para><b>CP</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>SP</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>GP</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>PP</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Copper piece (cp) =</para></cell>
<cell><para>1</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/10</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/100</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/1,000</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Silver piece (sp) =</para></cell>
<cell><para>10</para></cell>
<cell><para>1</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/10</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/100</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Gold piece (gp) =</para></cell>
<cell><para>100</para></cell>
<cell><para>10</para></cell>
<cell><para>1</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/10</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Platinum piece (pp) =</para></cell>
<cell><para>1,000</para></cell>
<cell><para>100</para></cell>
<cell><para>10</para></cell>
<cell><para>1</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Wealth Other Than Coins" origname="Wealth Other Than Coins" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Wealth_and_Money_Wealth_Other_Than_Coins" docbookid="Equipment4" refname="Wealth Other Than Coins" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="coin,equip,gear,monei,wealth"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Wealth Other Than Coins" style="heading 3">Wealth Other Than Coins</para><para>Merchants commonly exchange trade goods without using currency. As a means of comparison, some trade goods are detailed below.</para><para/><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Table: Trade Goods</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of wheat</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>2 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of flour, or one chicken</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of iron</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of tobacco or copper</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of cinnamon, or one goat</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of ginger or pepper, or one sheep</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>3 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pig</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>4 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One square yard of linen</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of salt or silver</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One square yard of silk, or one cow</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of saffron or cloves, or one ox</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of gold</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>500 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>One pound of platinum</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Selling Loot" origname="Selling Loot" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Wealth_and_Money_Selling_Loot" docbookid="Equipment5" refname="Selling Loot" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,loot,monei,sell,wealth"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Selling Loot" style="heading 3">Selling Loot</para><para>In general, a character can sell something for half its listed price.</para><para>Trade goods are the exception to the half-price rule. A trade good, in this sense, is a valuable good that can be easily exchanged almost as if it were cash itself.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="2" name="Weapons" origname="Weapons" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons" docbookid="Equipment6" refname="Weapons" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Weapons" style="heading 2">Weapons</para><topic level="3" name="Weapon Categories" origname="Weapon Categories" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Categories" docbookid="Equipment7" refname="Weapon Categories" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="categori,equip,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Weapon Categories" style="heading 3">Weapon Categories</para><para>Weapons are grouped into several interlocking sets of categories.</para><para>These categories pertain to what training is needed to become proficient in a weapon's use (simple, martial, or exotic), the weapon's usefulness either in close combat (melee) or at a distance (ranged, which includes both thrown and projectile weapons), its relative encumbrance (light, one-handed, or two-handed), and its size (Small, Medium, or Large).</para><topic level="8" name="Simple, Martial, and Exotic Weapons" origname="Simple, Martial, and Exotic Weapons" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Categories_Simple_Martial_and_Exotic_Weapons" docbookid="Equipment8" refname="Simple, Martial, and Exotic Weapons" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="categori,equip,exot,gear,martial,simpl,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Simple, Martial, and Exotic Weapons"><b>Simple, Martial, and Exotic Weapons:</b> Anybody but a druid, monk, rogue, or wizard is proficient with all simple weapons. Barbarians, fighters, paladins, and rangers are proficient with all simple and all martial weapons. Characters of other classes are proficient with an assortment of mainly simple weapons and possibly also some martial or even exotic weapons. A character who uses a weapon with which he or she is not proficient takes a -4 penalty on attack rolls.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Melee and Ranged Weapons" origname="Melee and Ranged Weapons" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Categories_Melee_and_Ranged_Weapons" docbookid="Equipment9" refname="Melee and Ranged Weapons" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="categori,equip,gear,mele,rang,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Melee and Ranged Weapons"><b>Melee and Ranged Weapons:</b> Melee weapons are used for making melee attacks, though some of them can be thrown as well. Ranged weapons are thrown weapons or projectile weapons that are not effective in melee.</para><para><i>Reach Weapons:</i> Glaives, guisarmes, lances, longspears, ranseurs, spiked chains, and whips are reach weapons. A reach weapon is a melee weapon that allows its wielder to strike at targets that aren't adjacent to him or her. Most reach double the wielder's natural reach, meaning that a typical Small or Medium wielder of such a weapon can attack a creature 10 feet away, but not a creature in an adjacent square. A typical Large character wielding a reach weapon of the appropriate size can attack a creature 15 or 20 feet away, but not adjacent creatures or creatures up to 10 feet away.</para><para><i>Double Weapons:</i> Dire flails, dwarven urgroshes, gnome hooked hammers, orc double axes, quarterstaffs, and two-bladed swords are double weapons. A character can fight with both ends of a double weapon as if fighting with two weapons, but he or she incurs all the normal attack penalties associated with two-weapon combat, just as though the character were wielding a one-handed weapon and a light weapon.</para><para>The character can also choose to use a double weapon two handed, attacking with only one end of it. A creature wielding a double weapon in one hand can't use it as a double weapon-only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.</para><para><i>Thrown Weapons:</i> Daggers, clubs, shortspears, spears, darts, javelins, throwing axes, light hammers, tridents, shuriken, and nets are thrown weapons. The wielder applies his or her Strength modifier to damage dealt by thrown weapons (except for splash weapons). It is possible to throw a weapon that isn't designed to be thrown (that is, a melee weapon that doesn't have a numeric entry in the Range Increment column on Table: Weapons), but a character who does so takes a -4 penalty on the attack roll. Throwing a light or one-handed weapon is a standard action, while throwing a two-handed weapon is a full-round action. Regardless of the type of weapon, such an attack scores a threat only on a natural roll of 20 and deals double damage on a critical hit. Such a weapon has a range increment of 10 feet.</para><para><i>Projectile Weapons:</i> Light crossbows, slings, heavy crossbows, shortbows, composite shortbows, longbows, composite longbows, hand crossbows, and repeating crossbows are projectile weapons. Most projectile weapons require two hands to use (see specific weapon descriptions). A character gets no Strength bonus on damage rolls with a projectile weapon unless it's a specially built composite shortbow, specially built composite longbow, or sling. If the character has a penalty for low Strength, apply it to damage rolls when he or she uses a bow or a sling.</para><para><i>Ammunition:</i> Projectile weapons use ammunition: arrows (for bows), bolts (for crossbows), or sling bullets (for slings). When using a bow, a character can draw ammunition as a free action; crossbows and slings require an action for reloading. Generally speaking, ammunition that hits its target is destroyed or rendered useless, while normal ammunition that misses has a 50% chance of being destroyed or lost.</para><para>Although they are thrown weapons, shuriken are treated as ammunition for the purposes of drawing them, crafting masterwork or otherwise special versions of them (see Masterwork Weapons), and what happens to them after they are thrown.</para><para/>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Light, One-Handed, and Two-Handed Melee Weapons" origname="Light, One-Handed, and Two-Handed Melee Weapons" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Categories_Light_One_Handed_and_Two_Handed_Melee_Weapons" docbookid="Equipment10" refname="Light, One-Handed, and Two-Handed Melee Weapons" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="categori,equip,gear,light,mele,one-handed,two-handed,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Light, One-Handed, and Two-Handed Melee Weapons"><b>Light, One-Handed, and Two-Handed Melee Weapons:</b> This designation is a measure of how much effort it takes to wield a weapon in combat. It indicates whether a melee weapon, when wielded by a character of the weapon's size category, is considered a light weapon, a one-handed weapon, or a two-handed weapon.</para><para><i>Light:</i> A light weapon is easier to use in one's off hand than a one-handed weapon is, and it can be used while grappling. A light weapon is used in one hand. Add the wielder's Strength bonus (if any) to damage rolls for melee attacks with a light weapon if it's used in the primary hand, or one-half the wielder's Strength bonus if it's used in the off hand. Using two hands to wield a light weapon gives no advantage on damage; the Strength bonus applies as though the weapon were held in the wielder's primary hand only.</para><para>An unarmed strike is always considered a light weapon.</para><para><i>One-Handed:</i> A one-handed weapon can be used in either the primary hand or the off hand. Add the wielder's Strength bonus to damage rolls for melee attacks with a one-handed weapon if it's used in the primary hand, or 1/2 his or her Strength bonus if it's used in the off hand. If a one-handed weapon is wielded with two hands during melee combat, add 1-1/2 times the character's Strength bonus to damage rolls.</para><para><i>Two-Handed:</i> Two hands are required to use a two-handed melee weapon effectively. Apply 1-1/2 times the character's Strength bonus to damage rolls for melee attacks with such a weapon.</para><para/>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Weapon Size" origname="Weapon Size" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Categories_Weapon_Size" docbookid="Equipment11" refname="Weapon Size" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="categori,equip,gear,size,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Weapon Size"><b>Weapon Size:</b> Every weapon has a size category. This designation indicates the size of the creature for which the weapon was designed.</para><para>A weapon's size category isn't the same as its size as an object. Instead, a weapon's size category is keyed to the size of the intended wielder. In general, a light weapon is an object two size categories smaller than the wielder, a one-handed weapon is an object one size category smaller than the wielder, and a two-handed weapon is an object of the same size category as the wielder.</para><para><i>Inappropriately Sized Weapons:</i> A creature can't make optimum use of a weapon that isn't properly sized for it. A cumulative -2 penalty applies on attack rolls for each size category of difference between the size of its intended wielder and the size of its actual wielder. If the creature isn't proficient with the weapon a -4 nonproficiency penalty also applies.</para><para>The measure of how much effort it takes to use a weapon (whether the weapon is designated as a light, one-handed, or two-handed weapon for a particular wielder) is altered by one step for each size category of difference between the wielder's size and the size of the creature for which the weapon was designed. If a weapon's designation would be changed to something other than light, one-handed, or two-handed by this alteration, the creature can't wield the weapon at all.</para><para/>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Improvised Weapons" origname="Improvised Weapons" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Categories_Improvised_Weapons" docbookid="Equipment12" refname="Improvised Weapons" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="categori,equip,gear,improv,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Improvised Weapons"><b>Improvised Weapons:</b> Sometimes objects not crafted to be weapons nonetheless see use in combat. Because such objects are not designed for this use, any creature that uses one in combat is considered to be nonproficient with it and takes a -4 penalty on attack rolls made with that object. To determine the size category and appropriate damage for an improvised weapon, compare its relative size and damage potential to the weapon list to find a reasonable match. An improvised weapon scores a threat on a natural roll of 20 and deals double damage on a critical hit. An improvised thrown weapon has a range increment of 10 feet.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Weapon Qualities" origname="Weapon Qualities" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities" docbookid="Equipment13" refname="Weapon Qualities" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,qualiti,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Weapon Qualities" style="heading 3">Weapon Qualities</para><para>Here is the format for weapon entries (given as column headings on Table: Weapons, below).</para><topic level="8" name="Cost" origname="Cost" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities_Cost" docbookid="Equipment14" refname="Cost" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cost,equip,gear,qualiti,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Cost"><b>Cost:</b> This value is the weapon's cost in gold pieces (gp) or silver pieces (sp). The cost includes miscellaneous gear that goes with the weapon.</para><para>This cost is the same for a Small or Medium version of the weapon. A Large version costs twice the listed price.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Damage" origname="Damage" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities_Damage" docbookid="Equipment15" refname="Damage" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="damag,equip,gear,qualiti,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Damage"><b>Damage:</b> The Damage columns give the damage dealt by the weapon on a successful hit. The column labeled 'Dmg (S)' is for Small weapons. The column labeled 'Dmg (M)' is for Medium weapons. If two damage ranges are given then the weapon is a double weapon. Use the second damage figure given for the double weapon's extra attack. Table: Tiny and Large Weapon Damage gives weapon damage values for weapons of those sizes.</para><para/><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Table: Tiny and Large Weapon Damage</b></para></cell> <cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Medium Weapon Damage</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Tiny Weapon Damage</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Large Weapon Damage</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1d2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d2</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d6</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d8</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>1d12</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>3d6</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>2d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d6</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>2d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>3d6</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>2d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>3d8</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>2d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>4d8</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Critical" origname="Critical" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities_Critical" docbookid="Equipment16" refname="Critical" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="critic,equip,gear,qualiti,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Critical"><b>Critical:</b> The entry in this column notes how the weapon is used with the rules for critical hits. When your character scores a critical hit, roll the damage two, three, or four times, as indicated by its critical multiplier (using all applicable modifiers on each roll), and add all the results together.</para><para><i>Exception:</i> Extra damage over and above a weapon's normal damage is not multiplied when you score a critical hit.</para><para>x<i>2:</i> The weapon deals double damage on a critical hit.</para><para>x<i>3:</i> The weapon deals triple damage on a critical hit.</para><para>x<i>3/</i>x<i>4:</i> One head of this double weapon deals triple damage on a critical hit. The other head deals quadruple damage on a critical hit.</para><para>x<i>4:</i> The weapon deals quadruple damage on a critical hit.</para><para><i>19-20/</i>x<i>2:</i> The weapon scores a threat on a natural roll of 19 or 20 (instead of just 20) and deals double damage on a critical hit. (The weapon has a threat range of 19-20.)</para><para><i>18-20/</i>x<i>2:</i> The weapon scores a threat on a natural roll of 18, 19, or 20 (instead of just 20) and deals double damage on a critical hit. (The weapon has a threat range of 18-20.)</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Range Increment" origname="Range Increment" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities_Range_Increment" docbookid="Equipment17" refname="Range Increment" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,increm,qualiti,rang,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Range Increment"><b>Range Increment:</b> Any attack at less than this distance is not penalized for range. However, each full range increment imposes a cumulative -2 penalty on the attack roll. A thrown weapon has a maximum range of five range increments. A projectile weapon can shoot out to ten range increments.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Weight" origname="Weight" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities_Weight" docbookid="Equipment18" refname="Weight" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,qualiti,weapon,weight"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Weight"><b>Weight:</b> This column gives the weight of a Medium version of the weapon. Halve this number for Small weapons and double it for Large weapons.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Type" origname="Type" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities_Type" docbookid="Equipment19" refname="Type" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,qualiti,type,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Type"><b>Type:</b> Weapons are classified according to the type of damage they deal: bludgeoning, piercing, or slashing. Some monsters may be resistant or immune to attacks from certain types of weapons.</para><para>Some weapons deal damage of multiple types. If a weapon is of two types, the damage it deals is not half one type and half another; all of it is both types. Therefore, a creature would have to be immune to both types of damage to ignore any of the damage from such a weapon.</para><para>In other cases, a weapon can deal either of two types of damage. In a situation when the damage type is significant, the wielder can choose which type of damage to deal with such a weapon.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Special" origname="Special" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Qualities_Special" docbookid="Equipment20" refname="Special" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,qualiti,special,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Special"><b>Special:</b> Some weapons have special features. See the weapon descriptions for details.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Weapon Descriptions" origname="Weapon Descriptions" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions" docbookid="Equipment21" refname="Weapon Descriptions" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Weapon Descriptions" style="heading 3">Weapon Descriptions</para><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Table: Weapons</b></para></cell> <cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Simple Weapons</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Dmg (S)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Dmg (M)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Critical</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Range Increment</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b>
<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Type</b>
<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Unarmed Attacks</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Gauntlet</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d2</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Unarmed strike</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d2<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Light Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Dagger</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing or slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Dagger, punching</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Gauntlet, spiked</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Mace, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sickle</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>One-Handed Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Club</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Mace, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Morningstar</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning and piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shortspear</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Two-Handed Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Longspear<sup><b>4</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>9 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Quarterstaff<sup><b>5</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4/1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6/1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spear</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Ranged Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Crossbow, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>120 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bolts, crossbow (10)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Crossbow, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>35 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>80 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bolts, crossbow (10)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Dart</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Javelin</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sling</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>0 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bullets, sling (10)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Martial Weapons</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Dmg (S)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Dmg (M)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Critical</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Range Increment</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b><sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Type</b>
<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Light Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Axe, throwing</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Hammer, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Handaxe</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Kukri</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>18-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Pick, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x4</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sap</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d2</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spiked armor</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spiked shield, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sword, short</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>One-Handed Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Battleaxe</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Flail</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Longsword</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Pick, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x4</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Rapier</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>18-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Scimitar</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>18-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spiked shield, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>special</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Trident</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Warhammer</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Two-Handed Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Falchion</para></cell>
<cell><para>75 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>18-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Glaive<sup><b>4</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Greataxe</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d12</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Greatclub</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Flail, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Greatsword</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Guisarme<sup><b>4</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>9 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Halberd</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing or slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lance<sup><b>4</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Ranseur<sup><b>4</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Scythe</para></cell>
<cell><para>18 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x4</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing or slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Ranged Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Longbow</para></cell>
<cell><para>75 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Arrows (20)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Longbow, composite</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>110 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Arrows (20)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shortbow</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>60 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Arrows (20)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shortbow, composite</para></cell>
<cell><para>75 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>70 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Arrows (20)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Exotic Weapons</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Dmg (S)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Dmg (M)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Critical</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Range Increment</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b>
<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Type</b>
<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Light Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Kama</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Nunchaku</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sai</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Siangham</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>One-Handed Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Sword, bastard</para></cell>
<cell><para>35 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Waraxe, dwarven</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Whip<sup><b>4</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d2<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Two-Handed Melee Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Axe, orc double<sup><b>5</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>60 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6/1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8/1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Chain, spiked<sup><b>4</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>25 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>2d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Flail, dire<sup><b>5</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>90 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6/1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8/1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Hammer,</para>
<para>gnome hooked<sup><b>5</b></sup></para></cell> <cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6/1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8/1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3/x4</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning and piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sword, two-bladed<sup><b>5</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6/1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8/1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Urgrosh, dwarven<sup><b>5</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6/1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8/1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>x3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Slashing or piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><i>Ranged Weapons</i></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>Bolas</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Bludgeoning</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Crossbow, hand</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d3</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bolts (10)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Crossbow,</para>
<para>repeating heavy</para></cell> <cell><para>400 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d10</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>120 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bolts (5)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Crossbow,</para>
<para>repeating light</para></cell> <cell><para>250 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d6</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d8</para></cell>
<cell><para>19-20/x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>80 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bolts (5)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Net</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shuriken (5)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1</para></cell>
<cell><para>1d2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell><para>Piercing</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>1 Weight figures are for Medium weapons. A Small weapon weighs half as much, and a Large weapon weighs twice as much.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>2 When two types are given, the weapon is both types if the entry specifies 'and,' or either type (player's choice at time of attack) if the entry specifies 'or.'</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>3 The weapon deals nonlethal damage rather than lethal damage.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>4 Reach weapon.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>5 Double weapon.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/><para>Weapons found on Table: Weapons that have special options for the wielder ('you') are described below. Splash weapons are described under Special Substances and Items.</para><topic level="8" name="Arrows" origname="Arrows" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Arrows" docbookid="Equipment22" refname="Arrows" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="arrow,descript,equip,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Arrows"><b>Arrows:</b> An arrow used as a melee weapon is treated as a light improvised weapon (-4 penalty on attack rolls) and deals damage as a dagger of its size (critical multiplier x2). Arrows come in a leather quiver that holds 20 arrows. An arrow that hits its target is destroyed; one that misses has a 50% chance of being destroyed or lost.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Axe, Orc Double" origname="Axe, Orc Double" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Axe_Orc_Double" docbookid="Equipment23" refname="Axe, Orc Double" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="ax,descript,doubl,equip,gear,orc,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Axe, Orc Double"><b>Axe, Orc Double:</b> An orc double axe is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon.</para><para>A creature wielding an orc double axe in one hand can't use it as a double weapon-only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Bolas" origname="Bolas" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Bolas" docbookid="Equipment24" refname="Bolas" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="bola,descript,equip,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Bolas"><b>Bolas:</b> You can use this weapon to make a ranged trip attack against an opponent. You can't be tripped during your own trip attempt when using a set of bolas.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Bolts" origname="Bolts" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Bolts" docbookid="Equipment25" refname="Bolts" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="bolt,descript,equip,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Bolts"><b>Bolts:</b> A crossbow bolt used as a melee weapon is treated as a light improvised weapon (-4 penalty on attack rolls) and deals damage as a dagger of its size (crit x2). Bolts come in a wooden case that holds 10 bolts (or 5, for a repeating crossbow). A bolt that hits its target is destroyed; one that misses has a 50% chance of being destroyed or lost.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Bullets, Sling" origname="Bullets, Sling" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Bullets_Sling" docbookid="Equipment26" refname="Bullets, Sling" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="bullet,descript,equip,gear,sling,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Bullets, Sling"><b>Bullets, Sling:</b> Bullets come in a leather pouch that holds 10 bullets. A bullet that hits its target is destroyed; one that misses has a 50% chance of being destroyed or lost.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Chain, Spiked" origname="Chain, Spiked" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Chain_Spiked" docbookid="Equipment27" refname="Chain, Spiked" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="chain,descript,equip,gear,spike,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Chain, Spiked"><b>Chain, Spiked:</b> A spiked chain has reach, so you can strike opponents 10 feet away with it. In addition, unlike most other weapons with reach, it can be used against an adjacent foe.</para><para>You can make trip attacks with the chain. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the chain to avoid being tripped.</para><para>When using a spiked chain, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an opponent (including the roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).</para><para>You can use the Weapon Finesse feat to apply your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier to attack rolls with a spiked chain sized for you, even though it isn't a light weapon for you.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Crossbow, Hand" origname="Crossbow, Hand" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Crossbow_Hand" docbookid="Equipment28" refname="Crossbow, Hand" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="crossbow,descript,equip,gear,hand,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Crossbow, Hand"><b>Crossbow, Hand:</b> You can draw a hand crossbow back by hand. Loading a hand crossbow is a move action that provokes attacks of opportunity.</para><para>You can shoot, but not load, a hand crossbow with one hand at no penalty. You can shoot a hand crossbow with each hand, but you take a penalty on attack rolls as if attacking with two light weapons.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Crossbow, Heavy" origname="Crossbow, Heavy" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Crossbow_Heavy" docbookid="Equipment29" refname="Crossbow, Heavy" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="crossbow,descript,equip,gear,heavi,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Crossbow, Heavy"><b>Crossbow, Heavy:</b> You draw a heavy crossbow back by turning a small winch. Loading a heavy crossbow is a full-round action that provokes attacks of opportunity.</para><para>Normally, operating a heavy crossbow requires two hands. However, you can shoot, but not load, a heavy crossbow with one hand at a -4 penalty on attack rolls. You can shoot a heavy crossbow with each hand, but you take a penalty on attack rolls as if attacking with two one-handed weapons. This penalty is cumulative with the penalty for one-handed firing.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Crossbow, Light" origname="Crossbow, Light" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Crossbow_Light" docbookid="Equipment30" refname="Crossbow, Light" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="crossbow,descript,equip,gear,light,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Crossbow, Light"><b>Crossbow, Light:</b> You draw a light crossbow back by pulling a lever. Loading a light crossbow is a move action that provokes attacks of opportunity.</para><para>Normally, operating a light crossbow requires two hands. However, you can shoot, but not load, a light crossbow with one hand at a -2 penalty on attack rolls. You can shoot a light crossbow with each hand, but you take a penalty on attack rolls as if attacking with two light weapons. This penalty is cumulative with the penalty for one-handed firing.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Crossbow, Repeating" origname="Crossbow, Repeating" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Crossbow_Repeating" docbookid="Equipment31" refname="Crossbow, Repeating" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="crossbow,descript,equip,gear,repeat,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Crossbow, Repeating"><b>Crossbow, Repeating:</b> The repeating crossbow (whether heavy or light) holds 5 crossbow bolts. As long as it holds bolts, you can reload it by pulling the reloading lever (a free action). Loading a new case of 5 bolts is a full-round action that provokes attacks of opportunity.</para><para>You can fire a repeating crossbow with one hand or fire a repeating crossbow in each hand in the same manner as you would a normal crossbow of the same size. However, you must fire the weapon with two hands in order to use the reloading lever, and you must use two hands to load a new case of bolts.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Dagger" origname="Dagger" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Dagger" docbookid="Equipment32" refname="Dagger" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="dagger,descript,equip,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Dagger"><b>Dagger:</b> You get a +2 bonus on Sleight of Hand checks made to conceal a dagger on your body (see the Sleight of Hand skill).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Flail, Dire" origname="Flail, Dire" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Flail_Dire" docbookid="Equipment33" refname="Flail, Dire" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,dire,equip,flail,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Flail, Dire"><b>Flail, Dire:</b> A dire flail is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon. A creature wielding a dire flail in one hand can't use it as a double weapon- only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.</para><para>When using a dire flail, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an enemy (including the opposed attack roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).</para><para>You can also use this weapon to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the dire flail to avoid being tripped.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Flail or Heavy Flail" origname="Flail or Heavy Flail" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Flail_or_Heavy_Flail" docbookid="Equipment34" refname="Flail or Heavy Flail" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,flail,gear,heavi,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Flail or Heavy Flail"><b>Flail or Heavy Flail:</b> With a flail, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an enemy (including the roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).</para><para>You can also use this weapon to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the flail to avoid being tripped.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Gauntlet" origname="Gauntlet" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Gauntlet" docbookid="Equipment35" refname="Gauntlet" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gauntlet,gear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Gauntlet"><b>Gauntlet:</b> This metal glove lets you deal lethal damage rather than nonlethal damage with unarmed strikes. A strike with a gauntlet is otherwise considered an unarmed attack. The cost and weight given are for a single gauntlet. Medium and heavy armors (except breastplate) come with gauntlets.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Gauntlet, Spiked" origname="Gauntlet, Spiked" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Gauntlet_Spiked" docbookid="Equipment36" refname="Gauntlet, Spiked" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gauntlet,gear,spike,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Gauntlet, Spiked"><b>Gauntlet, Spiked:</b> Your opponent cannot use a disarm action to disarm you of spiked gauntlets. The cost and weight given are for a single gauntlet. An attack with a spiked gauntlet is considered an armed attack.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Glaive" origname="Glaive" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Glaive" docbookid="Equipment37" refname="Glaive" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,glaiv,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Glaive"><b>Glaive:</b> A glaive has reach. You can strike opponents 10 feet away with it, but you can't use it against an adjacent foe.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Guisarme" origname="Guisarme" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Guisarme" docbookid="Equipment38" refname="Guisarme" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,guisarm,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Guisarme"><b>Guisarme:</b> A guisarme has reach. You can strike opponents 10 feet away with it, but you can't use it against an adjacent foe.</para><para>You can also use it to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the guisarme to avoid being tripped.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Halberd" origname="Halberd" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Halberd" docbookid="Equipment39" refname="Halberd" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,halberd,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Halberd"><b>Halberd:</b> If you use a ready action to set a halberd against a charge, you deal double damage on a successful hit against a charging character.</para><para>You can use a halberd to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the halberd to avoid being tripped.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Hammer, Gnome Hooked" origname="Hammer, Gnome Hooked" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Hammer_Gnome_Hooked" docbookid="Equipment40" refname="Hammer, Gnome Hooked" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,gnome,hammer,hook,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Hammer, Gnome Hooked"><b>Hammer, Gnome Hooked:</b> A gnome hooked hammer is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon. The hammer's blunt head is a bludgeoning weapon that deals 1d6 points of damage (crit x3). Its hook is a piercing weapon that deals 1d4 points of damage (crit x4). You can use either head as the primary weapon. The other head is the offhand weapon. A creature wielding a gnome hooked hammer in one hand can't use it as a double weapon-only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.</para><para>You can use a gnome hooked hammer to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the gnome hooked hammer to avoid being tripped.</para><para>Gnomes treat gnome hooked hammers as martial weapons.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Javelin" origname="Javelin" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Javelin" docbookid="Equipment41" refname="Javelin" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,javelin,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Javelin"><b>Javelin:</b> Since it is not designed for melee, you are treated as nonproficient with it and take a -4 penalty on attack rolls if you use a javelin as a melee weapon.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Kama" origname="Kama" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Kama" docbookid="Equipment42" refname="Kama" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,kama,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Kama"><b>Kama:</b> The kama is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a kama special options.</para><para>You can use a kama to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the kama to avoid being tripped.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Lance" origname="Lance" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Lance" docbookid="Equipment43" refname="Lance" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,lanc,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Lance"><b>Lance:</b> A lance deals double damage when used from the back of a charging mount. It has reach, so you can strike opponents 10 feet away with it, but you can't use it against an adjacent foe.</para><para>While mounted, you can wield a lance with one hand.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Longbow" origname="Longbow" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Longbow" docbookid="Equipment44" refname="Longbow" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,longbow,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Longbow"><b>Longbow:</b> You need at least two hands to use a bow, regardless of its size. A longbow is too unwieldy to use while you are mounted. If you have a penalty for low Strength, apply it to damage rolls when you use a longbow. If you have a bonus for high Strength, you can apply it to damage rolls when you use a composite longbow (see below) but not a regular longbow.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Longbow, Composite" origname="Longbow, Composite" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Longbow_Composite" docbookid="Equipment45" refname="Longbow, Composite" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="composit,descript,equip,gear,longbow,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Longbow, Composite"><b>Longbow, Composite:</b> You need at least two hands to use a bow, regardless of its size. You can use a composite longbow while mounted. All composite bows are made with a particular strength rating (that is, each requires a minimum Strength modifier to use with proficiency). If your Strength bonus is less than the strength rating of the composite bow, you can't effectively use it, so you take a -2 penalty on attacks with it. The default composite longbow requires a Strength modifier of +0 or higher to use with proficiency. A composite longbow can be made with a high strength rating to take advantage of an above-average Strength score; this feature allows you to add your Strength bonus to damage, up to the maximum bonus indicated for the bow. Each point of Strength bonus granted by the bow adds 100 gp to its cost.</para><para>For purposes of weapon proficiency and similar feats, a composite longbow is treated as if it were a longbow.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Longspear" origname="Longspear" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Longspear" docbookid="Equipment46" refname="Longspear" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,longspear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Longspear"><b>Longspear:</b> A longspear has reach. You can strike opponents 10 feet away with it, but you can't use it against an adjacent foe. If you use a ready action to set a longspear against a charge, you deal double damage on a successful hit against a charging character.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Net" origname="Net" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Net" docbookid="Equipment47" refname="Net" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,net,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Net"><b>Net:</b> A net is used to entangle enemies. When you throw a net, you make a ranged touch attack against your target. A net's maximum range is 10 feet. If you hit, the target is entangled. An entangled creature takes a -2 penalty on attack rolls and a -4 penalty on Dexterity, can move at only half speed, and cannot charge or run. If you control the trailing rope by succeeding on an opposed Strength check while holding it, the entangled creature can move only within the limits that the rope allows. If the entangled creature attempts to cast a spell, it must make a DC 15 Concentration check or be unable to cast the spell.</para><para>An entangled creature can escape with a DC 20 Escape Artist check (a full-round action). The net has 5 hit points and can be burst with a DC 25 Strength check (also a full-round action).</para><para>A net is useful only against creatures within one size category of you.</para><para>A net must be folded to be thrown effectively. The first time you throw your net in a fight, you make a normal ranged touch attack roll. After the net is unfolded, you take a -4 penalty on attack rolls with it. It takes 2 rounds for a proficient user to fold a net and twice that long for a nonproficient one to do so.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Nunchaku" origname="Nunchaku" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Nunchaku" docbookid="Equipment48" refname="Nunchaku" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,nunchaku,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Nunchaku"><b>Nunchaku:</b> The nunchaku is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a nunchaku special options. With a nunchaku, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an enemy (including the roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Quarterstaff" origname="Quarterstaff" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Quarterstaff" docbookid="Equipment49" refname="Quarterstaff" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,quarterstaff,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Quarterstaff"><b>Quarterstaff:</b> A quarterstaff is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon. A creature wielding a quarterstaff in one hand can't use it as a double weapon-only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.</para><para>The quarterstaff is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a quarterstaff special options.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Ranseur" origname="Ranseur" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Ranseur" docbookid="Equipment50" refname="Ranseur" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,ranseur,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Ranseur"><b>Ranseur:</b> A ranseur has reach. You can strike opponents 10 feet away with it, but you can't use it against an adjacent foe.</para><para>With a ranseur, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an opponent (including the roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Rapier" origname="Rapier" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Rapier" docbookid="Equipment51" refname="Rapier" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,rapier,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Rapier"><b>Rapier:</b> You can use the Weapon Finesse feat to apply your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier to attack rolls with a rapier sized for you, even though it isn't a light weapon for you. You can't wield a rapier in two hands in order to apply 1-1/2 times your Strength bonus to damage.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sai" origname="Sai" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Sai" docbookid="Equipment52" refname="Sai" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,sai,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sai"><b>Sai:</b> With a sai, you get a +4 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an enemy (including the roll to avoid being disarmed if such an attempt fails).</para><para>The sai is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a sai special options.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Scythe" origname="Scythe" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Scythe" docbookid="Equipment53" refname="Scythe" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,scyth,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Scythe"><b>Scythe:</b> A scythe can be used to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the scythe to avoid being tripped.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shield, Heavy or Light" origname="Shield, Heavy or Light" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Shield_Heavy_or_Light" docbookid="Equipment54" refname="Shield, Heavy or Light" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,heavi,light,shield,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shield, Heavy or Light"><b>Shield, Heavy or Light:</b> You can bash with a shield instead of using it for defense. See Armor for details.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shortbow" origname="Shortbow" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Shortbow" docbookid="Equipment55" refname="Shortbow" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,shortbow,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shortbow"><b>Shortbow:</b> You need at least two hands to use a bow, regardless of its size. You can use a shortbow while mounted. If you have a penalty for low Strength, apply it to damage rolls when you use a shortbow. If you have a bonus for high Strength, you can apply it to damage rolls when you use a composite shortbow (see below) but not a regular shortbow.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shortbow, Composite" origname="Shortbow, Composite" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Shortbow_Composite" docbookid="Equipment56" refname="Shortbow, Composite" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="composit,descript,equip,gear,shortbow,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shortbow, Composite"><b>Shortbow, Composite:</b> You need at least two hands to use a bow, regardless of its size. You can use a composite shortbow while mounted. All composite bows are made with a particular strength rating (that is, each requires a minimum Strength modifier to use with proficiency). If your Strength bonus is lower than the strength rating of the composite bow, you can't effectively use it, so you take a -2 penalty on attacks with it. The default composite shortbow requires a Strength modifier of +0 or higher to use with proficiency. A composite shortbow can be made with a high strength rating to take advantage of an above-average Strength score; this feature allows you to add your Strength bonus to damage, up to the maximum bonus indicated for the bow. Each point of Strength bonus granted by the bow adds 75 gp to its cost.</para><para>For purposes of weapon proficiency and similar feats, a composite shortbow is treated as if it were a shortbow.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shortspear" origname="Shortspear" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Shortspear" docbookid="Equipment57" refname="Shortspear" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,shortspear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shortspear"><b>Shortspear:</b> A shortspear is small enough to wield one-handed. It may also be thrown.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shuriken" origname="Shuriken" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Shuriken" docbookid="Equipment58" refname="Shuriken" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,shuriken,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shuriken"><b>Shuriken:</b> A shuriken is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding shuriken special options. A shuriken can't be used as a melee weapon.</para><para>Although they are thrown weapons, shuriken are treated as ammunition for the purposes of drawing them, crafting masterwork or otherwise special versions of them and what happens to them after they are thrown.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Siangham" origname="Siangham" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Siangham" docbookid="Equipment59" refname="Siangham" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,siangham,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Siangham"><b>Siangham:</b> The siangham is a special monk weapon. This designation gives a monk wielding a siangham special options.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sickle" origname="Sickle" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Sickle" docbookid="Equipment60" refname="Sickle" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,sickl,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sickle"><b>Sickle:</b> A sickle can be used to make trip attacks. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the sickle to avoid being tripped.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sling" origname="Sling" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Sling" docbookid="Equipment61" refname="Sling" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,sling,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sling"><b>Sling:</b> Your Strength modifier applies to damage rolls when you use a sling, just as it does for thrown weapons. You can fire, but not load, a sling with one hand. Loading a sling is a move action that requires two hands and provokes attacks of opportunity.</para><para>You can hurl ordinary stones with a sling, but stones are not as dense or as round as bullets. Thus, such an attack deals damage as if the weapon were designed for a creature one size category smaller than you and you take a -1 penalty on attack rolls.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Spear" origname="Spear" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Spear" docbookid="Equipment62" refname="Spear" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,spear,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spear"><b>Spear:</b> A spear can be thrown. If you use a ready action to set a spear against a charge, you deal double damage on a successful hit against a charging character.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Spiked Armor" origname="Spiked Armor" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Spiked_Armor" docbookid="Equipment63" refname="Spiked Armor" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,spike,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spiked Armor"><b>Spiked Armor:</b> You can outfit your armor with spikes, which can deal damage in a grapple or as a separate attack. See Armor for details.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Spiked Shield, Heavy or Light" origname="Spiked Shield, Heavy or Light" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Spiked_Shield_Heavy_or_Light" docbookid="Equipment64" refname="Spiked Shield, Heavy or Light" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,heavi,light,shield,spike,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spiked Shield, Heavy or Light"><b>Spiked Shield, Heavy or Light:</b> You can bash with a spiked shield instead of using it for defense. See Armor for details.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Strike, Unarmed" origname="Strike, Unarmed" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Strike_Unarmed" docbookid="Equipment65" refname="Strike, Unarmed" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,strike,unarm,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Strike, Unarmed"><b>Strike, Unarmed:</b> A Medium character deals 1d3 points of nonlethal damage with an unarmed strike. A Small character deals 1d2 points of nonlethal damage. A monk or any character with the Improved Unarmed Strike feat can deal lethal or nonlethal damage with unarmed strikes, at her option. The damage from an unarmed strike is considered weapon damage for the purposes of effects that give you a bonus on weapon damage rolls.</para><para>An unarmed strike is always considered a light weapon. Therefore, you can use the Weapon Finesse feat to apply your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier to attack rolls with an unarmed strike.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sword, Bastard" origname="Sword, Bastard" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Sword_Bastard" docbookid="Equipment66" refname="Sword, Bastard" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="bastard,descript,equip,gear,sword,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sword, Bastard"><b>Sword, Bastard:</b> A bastard sword is too large to use in one hand without special training; thus, it is an exotic weapon. A character can use a bastard sword two-handed as a martial weapon.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sword, Two-Bladed" origname="Sword, Two-Bladed" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Sword_Two_Bladed" docbookid="Equipment67" refname="Sword, Two-Bladed" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,sword,two-bladed,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sword, Two-Bladed"><b>Sword, Two-Bladed:</b> A two-bladed sword is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon. A creature wielding a two-bladed sword in one hand can't use it as a double weapon-only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Trident" origname="Trident" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Trident" docbookid="Equipment68" refname="Trident" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,trident,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Trident"><b>Trident:</b> This weapon can be thrown. If you use a ready action to set a trident against a charge, you deal double damage on a successful hit against a charging character.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Urgrosh, Dwarven" origname="Urgrosh, Dwarven" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Urgrosh_Dwarven" docbookid="Equipment69" refname="Urgrosh, Dwarven" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,dwarven,equip,gear,urgrosh,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Urgrosh, Dwarven"><b>Urgrosh, Dwarven:</b> A dwarven urgrosh is a double weapon. You can fight with it as if fighting with two weapons, but if you do, you incur all the normal attack penalties associated with fighting with two weapons, just as if you were using a one-handed weapon and a light weapon. The urgrosh's axe head is a slashing weapon that deals 1d8 points of damage. Its spear head is a piercing weapon that deals 1d6 points of damage. You can use either head as the primary weapon. The other is the off-hand weapon. A creature wielding a dwarven urgrosh in one hand can't use it as a double weapon-only one end of the weapon can be used in any given round.</para><para>If you use a ready action to set an urgrosh against a charge, you deal double damage if you score a hit against a charging character. If you use an urgrosh against a charging character, the spear head is the part of the weapon that deals damage.</para><para>Dwarves treat dwarven urgroshes as martial weapons.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Waraxe, Dwarven" origname="Waraxe, Dwarven" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Waraxe_Dwarven" docbookid="Equipment70" refname="Waraxe, Dwarven" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,dwarven,equip,gear,warax,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Waraxe, Dwarven"><b>Waraxe, Dwarven:</b> A dwarven waraxe is too large to use in one hand without special training; thus, it is an exotic weapon. A Medium character can use a dwarven waraxe two-handed as a martial weapon, or a Large creature can use it one-handed in the same way. A dwarf treats a dwarven waraxe as a martial weapon even when using it in one hand.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Whip" origname="Whip" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Weapon_Descriptions_Whip" docbookid="Equipment71" refname="Whip" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="descript,equip,gear,weapon,whip"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Whip"><b>Whip:</b> A whip deals nonlethal damage. It deals no damage to any creature with an armor bonus of +1 or higher or a natural armor bonus of +3 or higher. The whip is treated as a melee weapon with 15-foot reach, though you don't threaten the area into which you can make an attack. In addition, unlike most other weapons with reach, you can use it against foes anywhere within your reach (including adjacent foes).</para><para>Using a whip provokes an attack of opportunity, just as if you had used a ranged weapon.</para><para>You can make trip attacks with a whip. If you are tripped during your own trip attempt, you can drop the whip to avoid being tripped.</para><para>When using a whip, you get a +2 bonus on opposed attack rolls made to disarm an opponent (including the roll to keep from being disarmed if the attack fails).</para><para>You can use the Weapon Finesse feat to apply your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier to attack rolls with a whip sized for you, even though it isn't a light weapon for you.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Masterwork Weapons" origname="Masterwork Weapons" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Weapons_Masterwork_Weapons" docbookid="Equipment72" refname="Masterwork Weapons" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,masterwork,weapon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Masterwork Weapons" style="heading 3">Masterwork Weapons</para><para>A masterwork weapon is a finely crafted version of a normal weapon. Wielding it provides a +1 enhancement bonus on attack rolls.</para><para>You can't add the masterwork quality to a weapon after it is created; it must be crafted as a masterwork weapon (see the Craft skill). The masterwork quality adds 300 gp to the cost of a normal weapon (or 6 gp to the cost of a single unit of ammunition). Adding the masterwork quality to a double weapon costs twice the normal increase (+600 gp).</para><para>Masterwork ammunition is damaged (effectively destroyed) when used. The enhancement bonus of masterwork ammunition does not stack with any enhancement bonus of the projectile weapon firing it.</para><para>All magic weapons are automatically considered to be of masterwork quality. The enhancement bonus granted by the masterwork quality doesn't stack with the enhancement bonus provided by the weapon's magic.</para><para>Even though some types of armor and shields can be used as weapons, you can't create a masterwork version of such an item that confers an enhancement bonus on attack rolls. Instead, masterwork armor and shields have lessened armor check penalties.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="2" name="Armor" origname="Armor" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor" docbookid="Equipment73" refname="Armor" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,equip,gear"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Armor" style="heading 2">Armor</para><para/><topic level="3" name="Armor Qualities" origname="Armor Qualities" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities" docbookid="Equipment74" refname="Armor Qualities" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,equip,gear,qualiti"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Armor Qualities" style="heading 3">Armor Qualities</para><para>To wear heavier armor effectively, a character can select the Armor Proficiency feats, but most classes are automatically proficient with the armors that work best for them.</para><para>Armor and shields can take damage from some types of attacks.</para><para>Here is the format for armor entries (given as column headings on Table: Armor and Shields, below).</para><topic level="8" name="Cost" origname="Cost" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities_Cost" docbookid="Equipment75" refname="Cost" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,cost,equip,gear,qualiti"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Cost"><b>Cost:</b> The cost of the armor for Small or Medium humanoid creatures. See Armor for Unusual Creatures, below, for armor prices for other creatures.</para><para/>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Armor/Shield Bonus" origname="Armor/Shield Bonus" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities_Armor_Shield_Bonus" docbookid="Equipment76" refname="Armor/Shield Bonus" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,armor/shield,bonu,equip,gear,qualiti"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Armor/Shield Bonus"><b>Armor/Shield Bonus:</b> Each armor grants an armor bonus to AC, while shields grant a shield bonus to AC. The armor bonus from a suit of armor doesn't stack with other effects or items that grant an armor bonus. Similarly, the shield bonus from a shield doesn't stack with other effects that grant a shield bonus.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Maximum Dex Bonus" origname="Maximum Dex Bonus" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities_Maximum_Dex_Bonus" docbookid="Equipment77" refname="Maximum Dex Bonus" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,bonu,dex,equip,gear,maximum,qualiti"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Maximum Dex Bonus"><b>Maximum Dex Bonus:</b> This number is the maximum Dexterity bonus to AC that this type of armor allows. Heavier armors limit mobility, reducing the wearer's ability to dodge blows. This restriction doesn't affect any other Dexterity-related abilities.</para><para>Even if a character's Dexterity bonus to AC drops to 0 because of armor, this situation does not count as losing a Dexterity bonus to AC.</para><para>Your character's encumbrance (the amount of gear he or she carries) may also restrict the maximum Dexterity bonus that can be applied to his or her Armor Class.</para><para><i>Shields:</i> Shields do not affect a character's maximum Dexterity bonus.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Armor Check Penalty" origname="Armor Check Penalty" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities_Armor_Check_Penalty" docbookid="Equipment78" refname="Armor Check Penalty" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,check,equip,gear,penalti,qualiti"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Armor Check Penalty"><b>Armor Check Penalty:</b> Any armor heavier than leather hurts a character's ability to use some skills. An armor check penalty number is the penalty that applies to Balance, Climb, Escape Artist, Hide, Jump, Move Silently, Sleight of Hand, and Tumble checks by a character wearing a certain kind of armor. Double the normal armor check penalty is applied to Swim checks. A character's encumbrance (the amount of gear carried, including armor) may also apply an armor check penalty.</para><para><i>Shields:</i> If a character is wearing armor and using a shield, both armor check penalties apply.</para><para><i>Nonproficient with Armor Worn:</i> A character who wears armor and/or uses a shield with which he or she is not proficient takes the armor's (and/or shield's) armor check penalty on attack rolls and on all Strength-based and Dexterity-based ability and skill checks. The penalty for nonproficiency with armor stacks with the penalty for nonproficiency with shields.</para><para><i>Sleeping in Armor:</i> A character who sleeps in medium or heavy armor is automatically fatigued the next day. He or she takes a -2 penalty on Strength and Dexterity and can't charge or run. Sleeping in light armor does not cause fatigue.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Arcane Spell Failure" origname="Arcane Spell Failure" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities_Arcane_Spell_Failure" docbookid="Equipment79" refname="Arcane Spell Failure" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="arcan,armor,equip,failur,gear,qualiti,spell"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Arcane Spell Failure"><b>Arcane Spell Failure:</b> Armor interferes with the gestures that a spellcaster must make to cast an arcane spell that has a somatic component. Arcane spellcasters face the possibility of arcane spell failure if they're wearing armor. Bards can wear light armor without incurring any arcane spell failure chance for their bard spells.</para><para><i>Casting an Arcane Spell in Armor:</i> A character who casts an arcane spell while wearing armor must usually make an arcane spell failure roll. The number in the Arcane Spell Failure Chance column on Table: Armor and Shields is the chance that the spell fails and is ruined. If the spell lacks a somatic component, however, it can be cast with no chance of arcane spell failure.</para><para><i>Shields:</i> If a character is wearing armor and using a shield, add the two numbers together to get a single arcane spell failure chance.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Speed" origname="Speed" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities_Speed" docbookid="Equipment80" refname="Speed" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,equip,gear,qualiti,spe"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Speed"><b>Speed:</b> Medium or heavy armor slows the wearer down. The number on Table: Armor and Shields is the character's speed while wearing the armor. Humans, elves, half-elves, and half-orcs have an unencumbered speed of 30 feet.</para><para>They use the first column. Dwarves, gnomes, and halflings have an unencumbered speed of 20 feet. They use the second column. Remember, however, that a dwarf's land speed remains 20 feet even in medium or heavy armor or when carrying a medium or heavy load.</para><para><i>Shields:</i> Shields do not affect a character's speed.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Weight" origname="Weight" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Qualities_Weight" docbookid="Equipment81" refname="Weight" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,equip,gear,qualiti,weight"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Weight"><b>Weight:</b> This column gives the weight of the armor sized for a Medium wearer. Armor fitted for Small characters weighs half as much, and armor for Large characters weighs twice as much.</para><para/><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Table: Armor and Shields</b></para></cell> <cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell><para><b>-- Speed --</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Armor</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Armor/Shield</b> </para>
<para><b>Bonus</b></para></cell> <cell><para><b>Maximum</b> </para>
<para><b>Dex Bonus</b></para></cell> <cell><para><b>Armor</b> </para>
<para><b>Check Penalty</b></para></cell> <cell><para><b>Arcane Spell</b> </para>
<para><b>Failure Chance</b></para></cell> <cell><para><b>(30 ft.)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>(20 ft.)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b>
<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Light armor</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Padded</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+1</para></cell>
<cell><para>+8</para></cell>
<cell><para>0</para></cell>
<cell><para>5%</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Leather</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+2</para></cell>
<cell><para>+6</para></cell>
<cell><para>0</para></cell>
<cell><para>10%</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Studded leather</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+3</para></cell>
<cell><para>+5</para></cell>
<cell><para>-1</para></cell>
<cell><para>15%</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Chain shirt</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+4</para></cell>
<cell><para>+4</para></cell>
<cell><para>-2</para></cell>
<cell><para>20%</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Medium armor</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Hide</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+3</para></cell>
<cell><para>+4</para></cell>
<cell><para>-3</para></cell>
<cell><para>20%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Scale mail</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+4</para></cell>
<cell><para>+3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-4</para></cell>
<cell><para>25%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Chainmail</para></cell>
<cell><para>150 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+5</para></cell>
<cell><para>+2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-5</para></cell>
<cell><para>30%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>40 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Breastplate</para></cell>
<cell><para>200 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+5</para></cell>
<cell><para>+3</para></cell>
<cell><para>-4</para></cell>
<cell><para>25%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Heavy armor</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Splint mail</para></cell>
<cell><para>200 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+6</para></cell>
<cell><para>+0</para></cell>
<cell><para>-7</para></cell>
<cell><para>40%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>45 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Banded mail</para></cell>
<cell><para>250 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+6</para></cell>
<cell><para>+1</para></cell>
<cell><para>-6</para></cell>
<cell><para>35%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>35 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Half-plate</para></cell>
<cell><para>600 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+7</para></cell>
<cell><para>+0</para></cell>
<cell><para>-7</para></cell>
<cell><para>40%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>50 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Full plate</para></cell>
<cell><para>1,500 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+8</para></cell>
<cell><para>+1</para></cell>
<cell><para>-6</para></cell>
<cell><para>35%</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>15 ft.<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>50 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shields</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Buckler</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+1</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-1</para></cell>
<cell><para>5%</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield, light wooden</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+1</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-1</para></cell>
<cell><para>5%</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield, light steel</para></cell>
<cell><para>9 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+1</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-1</para></cell>
<cell><para>5%</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield, heavy wooden</para></cell>
<cell><para>7 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-2</para></cell>
<cell><para>15%</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield, heavy steel</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-2</para></cell>
<cell><para>15%</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield, tower</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>+4<sup><b>3</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>+2</para></cell>
<cell><para>-10</para></cell>
<cell><para>50%</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>45 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Extras</para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Armor spikes</para></cell>
<cell><para>+50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>+10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Gauntlet, locked</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>Special</para></cell>
<cell><para><b>4</b></para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>+5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield spikes</para></cell>
<cell><para>+10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>+5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>1 Weight figures are for armor sized to fit Medium characters. Armor fitted for Small characters weighs half as much, and armor fitted for Large characters weighs twice as much.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>2 When running in heavy armor, you move only triple your speed, not quadruple.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>3 A tower shield can instead grant you cover. See the description.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>4 Hand not free to cast spells.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Armor Descriptions" origname="Armor Descriptions" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions" docbookid="Equipment82" refname="Armor Descriptions" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Armor Descriptions" style="heading 3">Armor Descriptions</para><para>Any special benefits or accessories to the types of armor found on Table: Armor and Shields are described below.</para><topic level="8" name="Armor Spikes" origname="Armor Spikes" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Armor_Spikes" docbookid="Equipment83" refname="Armor Spikes" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,spike"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Armor Spikes"><b>Armor Spikes:</b> You can have spikes added to your armor, which allow you to deal extra piercing damage (see Table: Weapons) on a successful grapple attack. The spikes count as a martial weapon. If you are not proficient with them, you take a -4 penalty on grapple checks when you try to use them. You can also make a regular melee attack (or off-hand attack) with the spikes, and they count as a light weapon in this case. (You can't also make an attack with armor spikes if you have already made an attack with another off-hand weapon, and vice versa.)</para><para>An enhancement bonus to a suit of armor does not improve the spikes' effectiveness, but the spikes can be made into magic weapons in their own right.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Banded Mail" origname="Banded Mail" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Banded_Mail" docbookid="Equipment84" refname="Banded Mail" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,band,descript,equip,gear,mail"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Banded Mail"><b>Banded Mail:</b> The suit includes gauntlets.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Breastplate" origname="Breastplate" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Breastplate" docbookid="Equipment85" refname="Breastplate" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,breastplat,descript,equip,gear"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Breastplate"><b>Breastplate:</b> It comes with a helmet and greaves.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Buckler" origname="Buckler" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Buckler" docbookid="Equipment86" refname="Buckler" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,buckler,descript,equip,gear"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Buckler"><b>Buckler:</b> This small metal shield is worn strapped to your forearm. You can use a bow or crossbow without penalty while carrying it. You can also use your shield arm to wield a weapon (whether you are using an off-hand weapon or using your off hand to help wield a two-handed weapon), but you take a -1 penalty on attack rolls while doing so. This penalty stacks with those that may apply for fighting with your off hand and for fighting with two weapons. In any case, if you use a weapon in your off hand, you don't get the buckler's AC bonus for the rest of the round.</para><para>You can't bash someone with a buckler.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Chain Shirt" origname="Chain Shirt" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Chain_Shirt" docbookid="Equipment87" refname="Chain Shirt" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,chain,descript,equip,gear,shirt"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Chain Shirt"><b>Chain Shirt:</b> A chain shirt comes with a steel cap.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Chainmail" origname="Chainmail" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Chainmail" docbookid="Equipment88" refname="Chainmail" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,chainmail,descript,equip,gear"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Chainmail"><b>Chainmail:</b> The suit includes gauntlets.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Full Plate" origname="Full Plate" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Full_Plate" docbookid="Equipment89" refname="Full Plate" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,full,gear,plate"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Full Plate"><b>Full Plate:</b> The suit includes gauntlets, heavy leather boots, a visored helmet, and a thick layer of padding that is worn underneath the armor. Each suit of full plate must be individually fitted to its owner by a master armorsmith, although a captured suit can be resized to fit a new owner at a cost of 200 to 800 (2d4x100) gold pieces.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Gauntlet, Locked" origname="Gauntlet, Locked" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Gauntlet_Locked" docbookid="Equipment90" refname="Gauntlet, Locked" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gauntlet,gear,lock"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Gauntlet, Locked"><b>Gauntlet, Locked:</b> This armored gauntlet has small chains and braces that allow the wearer to attach a weapon to the gauntlet so that it cannot be dropped easily. It provides a +10 bonus on any roll made to keep from being disarmed in combat. Removing a weapon from a locked gauntlet or attaching a weapon to a locked gauntlet is a full-round action that provokes attacks of opportunity.</para><para>The price given is for a single locked gauntlet. The weight given applies only if you're wearing a breastplate, light armor, or no armor. Otherwise, the locked gauntlet replaces a gauntlet you already have as part of the armor.</para><para>While the gauntlet is locked, you can't use the hand wearing it for casting spells or employing skills. (You can still cast spells with somatic components, provided that your other hand is free.)</para><para>Like a normal gauntlet, a locked gauntlet lets you deal lethal damage rather than nonlethal damage with an unarmed strike.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Half-Plate" origname="Half-Plate" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Half_Plate" docbookid="Equipment91" refname="Half-Plate" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,half-plate"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Half-Plate"><b>Half-Plate:</b> The suit includes gauntlets.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Scale Mail" origname="Scale Mail" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Scale_Mail" docbookid="Equipment92" refname="Scale Mail" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,mail,scale"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Scale Mail"><b>Scale Mail:</b> The suit includes gauntlets.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shield, Heavy, Wooden or Steel" origname="Shield, Heavy, Wooden or Steel" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Shield_Heavy_Wooden_or_Steel" docbookid="Equipment93" refname="Shield, Heavy, Wooden or Steel" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,heavi,shield,steel,wooden"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shield, Heavy, Wooden or Steel"><b>Shield, Heavy, Wooden or Steel:</b> You strap a shield to your forearm and grip it with your hand. A heavy shield is so heavy that you can't use your shield hand for anything else.</para><para><i>Wooden or Steel:</i> Wooden and steel shields offer the same basic protection, though they respond differently to special attacks.</para><para><i>Shield Bash Attacks:</i> You can bash an opponent with a heavy shield, using it as an off-hand weapon. See Table: Weapons for the damage dealt by a shield bash. Used this way, a heavy shield is a martial bludgeoning weapon. For the purpose of penalties on attack rolls, treat a heavy shield as a one-handed weapon. If you use your shield as a weapon, you lose its AC bonus until your next action (usually until the next round). An enhancement bonus on a shield does not improve the effectiveness of a shield bash made with it, but the shield can be made into a magic weapon in its own right.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shield, Light, Wooden or Steel" origname="Shield, Light, Wooden or Steel" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Shield_Light_Wooden_or_Steel" docbookid="Equipment94" refname="Shield, Light, Wooden or Steel" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,light,shield,steel,wooden"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shield, Light, Wooden or Steel"><b>Shield, Light, Wooden or Steel:</b> You strap a shield to your forearm and grip it with your hand. A light shield's weight lets you carry other items in that hand, although you cannot use weapons with it.</para><para><i>Wooden or Steel:</i> Wooden and steel shields offer the same basic protection, though they respond differently to special attacks.</para><para><i>Shield Bash Attacks:</i> You can bash an opponent with a light shield, using it as an off-hand weapon. See Table: Weapons for the damage dealt by a shield bash. Used this way, a light shield is a martial bludgeoning weapon. For the purpose of penalties on attack rolls, treat a light shield as a light weapon. If you use your shield as a weapon, you lose its AC bonus until your next action (usually until the next round). An enhancement bonus on a shield does not improve the effectiveness of a shield bash made with it, but the shield can be made into a magic weapon in its own right.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shield, Tower" origname="Shield, Tower" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Shield_Tower" docbookid="Equipment95" refname="Shield, Tower" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,shield,tower"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shield, Tower"><b>Shield, Tower:</b> This massive wooden shield is nearly as tall as you are. In most situations, it provides the indicated shield bonus to your AC. However, you can instead use it as total cover, though you must give up your attacks to do so. The shield does not, however, provide cover against targeted spells; a spellcaster can cast a spell on you by targeting the shield you are holding. You cannot bash with a tower shield, nor can you use your shield hand for anything else.</para><para>When employing a tower shield in combat, you take a -2 penalty on attack rolls because of the shield's encumbrance.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Shield Spikes" origname="Shield Spikes" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Shield_Spikes" docbookid="Equipment96" refname="Shield Spikes" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,shield,spike"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Shield Spikes"><b>Shield Spikes:</b> When added to your shield, these spikes turn it into a martial piercing weapon that increases the damage dealt by a shield bash as if the shield were designed for a creature one size category larger than you. You can't put spikes on a buckler or a tower shield. Otherwise, attacking with a spiked shield is like making a shield bash attack (see above).</para><para>An enhancement bonus on a spiked shield does not improve the effectiveness of a shield bash made with it, but a spiked shield can be made into a magic weapon in its own right.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Splint Mail" origname="Splint Mail" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_Descriptions_Splint_Mail" docbookid="Equipment97" refname="Splint Mail" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,descript,equip,gear,mail,splint"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Splint Mail"><b>Splint Mail:</b> The suit includes gauntlets.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Masterwork Armor" origname="Masterwork Armor" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Masterwork_Armor" docbookid="Equipment98" refname="Masterwork Armor" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,equip,gear,masterwork"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Masterwork Armor" style="heading 3">Masterwork Armor</para><para>Just as with weapons, you can purchase or craft masterwork versions of armor or shields. Such a well-made item functions like the normal version, except that its armor check penalty is lessened by 1.</para><para>A masterwork suit of armor or shield costs an extra 150 gp over and above the normal cost for that type of armor or shield.</para><para>The masterwork quality of a suit of armor or shield never provides a bonus on attack or damage rolls, even if the armor or shield is used as a weapon.</para><para>All magic armors and shields are automatically considered to be of masterwork quality.</para><para>You can't add the masterwork quality to armor or a shield after it is created; it must be crafted as a masterwork item.</para><para/>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Armor for Unusual Creatures" origname="Armor for Unusual Creatures" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Armor_for_Unusual_Creatures" docbookid="Equipment99" refname="Armor for Unusual Creatures" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,creatur,equip,gear,unusu"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Armor for Unusual Creatures" style="heading 3">Armor for Unusual Creatures</para><para>Armor and shields for unusually big creatures, unusually little creatures, and nonhumanoid creatures have different costs and weights from those given on Table: Armor and Shields. Refer to the appropriate line on the table below and apply the multipliers to cost and weight for the armor type in question.</para><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell><para><b>Humanoid</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Nonhumanoid</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Size</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Tiny or smaller<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>x1/2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1/10</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1/10</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Small</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1/2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1/2</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Medium</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Large</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Huge</para></cell>
<cell><para>x4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x5</para></cell>
<cell><para>x8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x5</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Gargantuan</para></cell>
<cell><para>x8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x8</para></cell>
<cell><para>x16</para></cell>
<cell><para>x8</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Colossal</para></cell>
<cell><para>x16</para></cell>
<cell><para>x12</para></cell>
<cell><para>x32</para></cell>
<cell><para>x12</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>1 Divide armor bonus by 2.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Getting into and Out of Armor" origname="Getting into and Out of Armor" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Getting_into_and_Out_of_Armor" docbookid="Equipment100" refname="Getting into and Out of Armor" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,equip,gear"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Getting into and Out of Armor" style="heading 3">Getting into and Out of Armor</para><para>The time required to don armor depends on its type; see Table: Donning Armor.</para><topic level="8" name="Don" origname="Don" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Getting_into_and_Out_of_Armor_Don" docbookid="Equipment101" refname="Don" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,don,equip,gear"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Don"><b>Don:</b> This column tells how long it takes a character to put the armor on. (One minute is 10 rounds.) Readying (strapping on) a shield is only a move action.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Don Hastily" origname="Don Hastily" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Getting_into_and_Out_of_Armor_Don_Hastily" docbookid="Equipment102" refname="Don Hastily" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,don,equip,gear,hastili"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Don Hastily"><b>Don Hastily:</b> This column tells how long it takes to put the armor on in a hurry. The armor check penalty and armor bonus for hastily donned armor are each 1 point worse than normal.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Remove" origname="Remove" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Armor_Getting_into_and_Out_of_Armor_Remove" docbookid="Equipment103" refname="Remove" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="armor,equip,gear,remov"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Remove"><b>Remove:</b> This column tells how long it takes to get the armor off. Loosing a shield (removing it from the arm and dropping it) is only a move action.</para><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Table: Donning Armor</b></para></cell> <cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Armor Type</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Don</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Don Hastily</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Remove</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Shield (any)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 move action</para></cell>
<cell><para>n/a</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 move action</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Padded, leather, hide, studded leather, or chain shirt</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 minute</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 rounds</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 minute<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Breastplate, scale mail, chainmail, banded mail, or splint mail</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 minutes<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>1 minute</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 minute<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Half-plate or full plate</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 minutes<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>4 minutes<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>1d4+1 minutes<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>1 If the character has some help, cut this time in half. A single character doing nothing else can help one or two adjacent characters. Two characters can't help each other don armor at the same time.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>2 The wearer must have help to don this armor. Without help, it can be donned only hastily.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/>
</topic>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="2" name="Goods and Services" origname="Goods and Services" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services" docbookid="Equipment104" refname="Goods and Services" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Goods and Services" style="heading 2">Goods and Services</para><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Table: Goods and Services</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Adventuring Gear</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Backpack (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Barrel (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Basket (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bedroll</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bell</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Blanket, winter</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Block and tackle</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bottle, wine, glass</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bucket (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Caltrops</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Candle</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Canvas (sq. yd.)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Case, map or scroll</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Chain (10 ft.)</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Chalk, 1 piece</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Chest (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Crowbar</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Firewood (per day)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Fishhook</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Fishing net, 25 sq. ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Flask (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1-1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Flint and steel</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Grappling hook</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Hammer</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Ink (1 oz. vial)</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Inkpen</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Jug, clay</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>9 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Ladder, 10-foot</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lamp, common</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lantern, bullseye</para></cell>
<cell><para>12 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lantern, hooded</para></cell>
<cell><para>7 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lock, Very simple</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lock, Average</para></cell>
<cell><para>40 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lock, Good</para></cell>
<cell><para>80 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Lock, Amazing</para></cell>
<cell><para>150 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Manacles</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Manacles, masterwork</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Mirror, small steel</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Mug/Tankard, clay</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Oil (1-pint flask)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Paper (sheet)</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Parchment (sheet)</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Pick, miner's</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Pitcher, clay</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Piton</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Pole, 10-foot</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Pot, iron</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Pouch, belt (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Ram, portable</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Rations, trail (per day)</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Rope, hempen (50 ft.)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Rope, silk (50 ft.)</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sack (empty)</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sealing wax</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sewing needle</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Signal whistle</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Signet ring</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sledge</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Soap (per lb.)</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spade or shovel</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spyglass</para></cell>
<cell><para>1,000 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Tent</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Torch</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Vial, ink or potion</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Waterskin</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Whetstone</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Special Substances and Items</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Acid (flask)</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Alchemist's fire (flask)</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Antitoxin (vial)</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Everburning torch</para></cell>
<cell><para>110 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Holy water (flask)</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Smokestick</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sunrod</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Tanglefoot bag</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Thunderstone</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Tindertwig</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Tools and Skill Kits</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Alchemist's lab</para></cell>
<cell><para>500 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>40 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Artisan's tools</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Artisan's tools, masterwork</para></cell>
<cell><para>55 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Climber's kit</para></cell>
<cell><para>80 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Disguise kit</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Healer's kit</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Holly and mistletoe</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Holy symbol, wooden</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Holy symbol, silver</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Hourglass</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Magnifying glass</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Musical instrument, common</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Musical instrument, masterwork</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Scale, merchant's</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell component pouch</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spellbook, wizard's (blank)</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Thieves' tools</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Thieves' tools, masterwork</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Tool, masterwork</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Water clock</para></cell>
<cell><para>1,000 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>200 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Clothing</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Artisan's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Cleric's vestments</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Cold weather outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>7 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Courtier's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Entertainer's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Explorer's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Monk's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Noble's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>75 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Peasant's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Royal outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>200 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Scholar's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Traveler's outfit</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 lb.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Food, Drink, and Lodging</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Ale, Gallon</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Ale, Mug</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Banquet (per person)</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bread, per loaf</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Cheese, hunk of</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Inn stay (per day), Good</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Inn stay (per day), Common</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Inn stay (per day), Poor</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Meals (per day), Good</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Meals (per day), Common</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Meals (per day), Poor</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Meat, chunk of</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Wine, Common (pitcher)</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>6 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Wine, Fine (bottle)</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1-1/2 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Mounts and Related Gear</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Barding, Medium creature</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell><para>x1</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Barding, Large creature</para></cell>
<cell><para>x4</para></cell>
<cell><para>x2</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Bit and bridle</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Dog, guard</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Dog, riding</para></cell>
<cell><para>150 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Donkey or mule</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Feed (per day)</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 cp</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Horse, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>200 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Horse, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>75 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Horse, Pony</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Horse, Warhorse, heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>400 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Horse, Warhorse, light</para></cell>
<cell><para>150 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Horse, Warpony</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Saddle, Military</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Saddle, Pack</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Saddle, Riding</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>25 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Saddle, Exotic, Military</para></cell>
<cell><para>60 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>40 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Saddle, Exotic, Pack</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Saddle, Exotic, Riding</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Saddlebags</para></cell>
<cell><para>4 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>8 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Stabling (per day)</para></cell>
<cell><para>5 sp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Transport</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Item</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Weight</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Carriage</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>600 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Cart</para></cell>
<cell><para>15 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>200 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Galley</para></cell>
<cell><para>30,000 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Keelboat</para></cell>
<cell><para>3,000 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Longship</para></cell>
<cell><para>10,000 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Rowboat</para></cell>
<cell><para>50 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>100 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Oar</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>10 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sailing ship</para></cell>
<cell><para>10,000 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Sled</para></cell>
<cell><para>20 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>300 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Wagon</para></cell>
<cell><para>35 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>400 lb.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Warship</para></cell>
<cell><para>25,000 gp</para></cell>
<cell><para>-</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Spellcasting and Services</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
<cell/>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Service</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>Cost</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Coach cab</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 cp per mile</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Hireling, trained</para></cell>
<cell><para>3 sp per day</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Hireling, untrained</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp per day</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Messenger</para></cell>
<cell><para>2 cp per mile</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Road or gate toll</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 cp</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Ship's passage</para></cell>
<cell><para>1 sp per mile</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 0-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x5 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 1st-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x10 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 2nd-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x20 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 3rd-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x30 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 4th-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x40 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 5th-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x50 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 6th-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x60 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 7th-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x70 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 8th-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x80 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Spell, 9th-level</para></cell>
<cell><para>Caster level x90 gp<sup><b>2</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>- No weight, or no weight worth noting.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>1 These items weigh one-quarter this amount when made for Small characters. Containers for Small characters also carry one-quarter the normal amount.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>2 See spell description for additional costs. If the additional costs put the spell's total cost above 3,000 gp, that spell is not generally available.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/><topic level="3" name="Adventuring Gear" origname="Adventuring Gear" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear" docbookid="Equipment105" refname="Adventuring Gear" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Adventuring Gear" style="heading 3">Adventuring Gear</para><para>few of the pieces of adventuring gear found on Table: Goods and Services are described below, along with any special benefits they confer on the user ('you').</para><topic level="8" name="Caltrops" origname="Caltrops" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Caltrops" docbookid="Equipment106" refname="Caltrops" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,caltrop,equip,gear,good,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Caltrops"><b>Caltrops:</b> A caltrop is a four-pronged iron spike crafted so that one prong faces up no matter how the caltrop comes to rest. You scatter caltrops on the ground in the hope that your enemies step on them or are at least forced to slow down to avoid them. One 2- pound bag of caltrops covers an area 5 feet square.</para><para>Each time a creature moves into an area covered by caltrops (or spends a round fighting while standing in such an area), it might step on one. The caltrops make an attack roll (base attack bonus +0) against the creature. For this attack, the creature's shield, armor, and deflection bonuses do not count. If the creature is wearing shoes or other footwear, it gets a +2 armor bonus to AC. If the caltrops succeed on the attack, the creature has stepped on one. The caltrop deals 1 point of damage, and the creature's speed is reduced by one-half because its foot is wounded. This movement penalty lasts for 24 hours, or until the creature is successfully treated with a DC 15 Heal check, or until it receives at least 1 point of magical curing. A charging or running creature must immediately stop if it steps on a caltrop. Any creature moving at half speed or slower can pick its way through a bed of caltrops with no trouble.</para><para>Caltrops may not be effective against unusual opponents.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Candle" origname="Candle" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Candle" docbookid="Equipment107" refname="Candle" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,candl,equip,gear,good,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Candle"><b>Candle:</b> A candle dimly illuminates a 5-foot radius and burns for 1 hour.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Chain" origname="Chain" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Chain" docbookid="Equipment108" refname="Chain" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,chain,equip,gear,good,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Chain"><b>Chain:</b> Chain has hardness 10 and 5 hit points. It can be burst with a DC 26 Strength check.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Crowbar" origname="Crowbar" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Crowbar" docbookid="Equipment109" refname="Crowbar" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,crowbar,equip,gear,good,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Crowbar"><b>Crowbar:</b> A crowbar it grants a +2 circumstance bonus on Strength checks made for such purposes. If used in combat, treat a crowbar as a one-handed improvised weapon that deals bludgeoning damage equal to that of a club of its size.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Flint and Steel" origname="Flint and Steel" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Flint_and_Steel" docbookid="Equipment110" refname="Flint and Steel" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,flint,gear,good,servic,steel"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Flint and Steel"><b>Flint and Steel:</b> Lighting a torch with flint and steel is a full-round action, and lighting any other fire with them takes at least that long.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Grappling Hook" origname="Grappling Hook" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Grappling_Hook" docbookid="Equipment111" refname="Grappling Hook" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,grappl,hook,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Grappling Hook"><b>Grappling Hook:</b> Throwing a grappling hook successfully requires a Use Rope check (DC 10, +2 per 10 feet of distance thrown).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Hammer" origname="Hammer" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Hammer" docbookid="Equipment112" refname="Hammer" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,hammer,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Hammer"><b>Hammer:</b> If a hammer is used in combat, treat it as a one-handed improvised weapon that deals bludgeoning damage equal to that of a spiked gauntlet of its size.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Ink" origname="Ink" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Ink" docbookid="Equipment113" refname="Ink" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,ink,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Ink"><b>Ink:</b> This is black ink. You can buy ink in other colors, but it costs twice as much.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Jug, Clay" origname="Jug, Clay" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Jug_Clay" docbookid="Equipment114" refname="Jug, Clay" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,clai,equip,gear,good,jug,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Jug, Clay"><b>Jug, Clay:</b> This basic ceramic jug is fitted with a stopper and holds 1 gallon of liquid.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Lamp, Common" origname="Lamp, Common" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Lamp_Common" docbookid="Equipment115" refname="Lamp, Common" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,common,equip,gear,good,lamp,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Lamp, Common"><b>Lamp, Common:</b> A lamp clearly illuminates a 15-foot radius, provides shadowy illumination out to a 30-foot radius, and burns for 6 hours on a pint of oil. You can carry a lamp in one hand.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Lantern, Bullseye" origname="Lantern, Bullseye" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Lantern_Bullseye" docbookid="Equipment116" refname="Lantern, Bullseye" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,bullsey,equip,gear,good,lantern,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Lantern, Bullseye"><b>Lantern, Bullseye:</b> A bullseye lantern provides clear illumination in a 60-foot cone and shadowy illumination in a 120-foot cone. It burns for 6 hours on a pint of oil. You can carry a bullseye lantern in one hand.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Lantern, Hooded" origname="Lantern, Hooded" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Lantern_Hooded" docbookid="Equipment117" refname="Lantern, Hooded" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,hood,lantern,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Lantern, Hooded"><b>Lantern, Hooded:</b> A hooded lantern clearly illuminates a 30-foot radius and provides shadowy illumination in a 60-foot radius. It burns for 6 hours on a pint of oil. You can carry a hooded lantern in one hand.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Lock" origname="Lock" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Lock" docbookid="Equipment118" refname="Lock" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,lock,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Lock"><b>Lock:</b> The DC to open a lock with the Open Lock skill depends on the lock's quality: simple (DC 20), average (DC 25), good (DC 30), or superior (DC 40).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Manacles and Manacles, Masterwork" origname="Manacles and Manacles, Masterwork" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Manacles_and_Manacles_Masterwork" docbookid="Equipment119" refname="Manacles and Manacles, Masterwork" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,manacl,masterwork,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Manacles and Manacles, Masterwork"><b>Manacles and Manacles, Masterwork:</b> Manacles can bind a Medium creature. A manacled creature can use the Escape Artist skill to slip free (DC 30, or DC 35 for masterwork manacles). Breaking the manacles requires a Strength check (DC 26, or DC 28 for masterwork manacles). Manacles have hardness 10 and 10 hit points.</para><para>Most manacles have locks; add the cost of the lock you want to the cost of the manacles.</para><para>For the same cost, you can buy manacles for a Small creature.</para><para>For a Large creature, manacles cost ten times the indicated amount, and for a Huge creature, one hundred times this amount. Gargantuan, Colossal, Tiny, Diminutive, and Fine creatures can be held only by specially made manacles.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Oil" origname="Oil" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Oil" docbookid="Equipment120" refname="Oil" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,oil,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Oil"><b>Oil:</b> A pint of oil burns for 6 hours in a lantern. You can use a flask of oil as a splash weapon. Use the rules for alchemist's fire, except that it takes a full round action to prepare a flask with a fuse. Once it is thrown, there is a 50% chance of the flask igniting successfully.</para><para>You can pour a pint of oil on the ground to cover an area 5 feet square, provided that the surface is smooth. If lit, the oil burns for 2 rounds and deals 1d3 points of fire damage to each creature in the area.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Ram, Portable" origname="Ram, Portable" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Ram_Portable" docbookid="Equipment121" refname="Ram, Portable" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,portabl,ram,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Ram, Portable"><b>Ram, Portable:</b> This iron-shod wooden beam gives you a +2 circumstance bonus on Strength checks made to break open a door and it allows a second person to help you without having to roll, increasing your bonus by 2.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Rope, Hempen" origname="Rope, Hempen" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Rope_Hempen" docbookid="Equipment122" refname="Rope, Hempen" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,hempen,rope,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Rope, Hempen"><b>Rope, Hempen:</b> This rope has 2 hit points and can be burst with a DC 23 Strength check.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Rope, Silk" origname="Rope, Silk" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Rope_Silk" docbookid="Equipment123" refname="Rope, Silk" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,rope,servic,silk"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Rope, Silk"><b>Rope, Silk:</b> This rope has 4 hit points and can be burst with a DC 24 Strength check. It is so supple that it provides a +2 circumstance bonus on Use Rope checks.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Spyglass" origname="Spyglass" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Spyglass" docbookid="Equipment124" refname="Spyglass" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,servic,spyglass"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spyglass"><b>Spyglass:</b> Objects viewed through a spyglass are magnified to twice their size.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Torch" origname="Torch" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Torch" docbookid="Equipment125" refname="Torch" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,servic,torch"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Torch"><b>Torch:</b> A torch burns for 1 hour, clearly illuminating a 20-foot radius and providing shadowy illumination out to a 40- foot radius. If a torch is used in combat, treat it as a one-handed improvised weapon that deals bludgeoning damage equal to that of a gauntlet of its size, plus 1 point of fire damage.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Vial" origname="Vial" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Adventuring_Gear_Vial" docbookid="Equipment126" refname="Vial" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="adventur,equip,gear,good,servic,vial"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Vial"><b>Vial:</b> A vial holds 1 ounce of liquid. The stoppered container usually is no more than 1 inch wide and 3 inches high.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Special Substances and Items" origname="Special Substances and Items" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items" docbookid="Equipment127" refname="Special Substances and Items" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Special Substances and Items" style="heading 3">Special Substances and Items</para><para>Any of these substances except for the everburning torch and holy water can be made by a character with the Craft (alchemy) skill.</para><topic level="8" name="Acid" origname="Acid" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Acid" docbookid="Equipment128" refname="Acid" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="acid,equip,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Acid"><b>Acid:</b> You can throw a flask of acid as a splash weapon. Treat this attack as a ranged touch attack with a range increment of 10 feet. A direct hit deals 1d6 points of acid damage. Every creature within 5 feet of the point where the acid hits takes 1 point of acid damage from the splash.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Alchemist's Fire" origname="Alchemist's Fire" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Alchemist_s_Fire" docbookid="Equipment129" refname="Alchemist's Fire" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="alchemist,equip,fire,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Alchemist's Fire"><b>Alchemist's Fire:</b> You can throw a flask of alchemist's fire as a splash weapon. Treat this attack as a ranged touch attack with a range increment of 10 feet.</para><para>A direct hit deals 1d6 points of fire damage. Every creature within 5 feet of the point where the flask hits takes 1 point of fire damage from the splash. On the round following a direct hit, the target takes an additional 1d6 points of damage. If desired, the target can use a full-round action to attempt to extinguish the flames before taking this additional damage. Extinguishing the flames requires a DC 15 Reflex save. Rolling on the ground provides the target a +2 bonus on the save. Leaping into a lake or magically extinguishing the flames automatically smothers the fire.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Antitoxin" origname="Antitoxin" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Antitoxin" docbookid="Equipment130" refname="Antitoxin" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="antitoxin,equip,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Antitoxin"><b>Antitoxin:</b> If you drink antitoxin, you get a +5 alchemical bonus on Fortitude saving throws against poison for 1 hour.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Everburning Torch" origname="Everburning Torch" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Everburning_Torch" docbookid="Equipment131" refname="Everburning Torch" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,everburn,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc,torch"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Everburning Torch"><b>Everburning Torch:</b> This otherwise normal torch has a <i>continual flame</i> spell cast upon it. An everburning torch clearly illuminates a 20-foot radius and provides shadowy illumination out to a 40-foot radius.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Holy Water" origname="Holy Water" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Holy_Water" docbookid="Equipment132" refname="Holy Water" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,holi,item,servic,special,substanc,water"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Holy Water"><b>Holy Water:</b> Holy water damages undead creatures and evil outsiders almost as if it were acid. A flask of holy water can be thrown as a splash weapon.</para><para>Treat this attack as a ranged touch attack with a range increment of 10 feet. A flask breaks if thrown against the body of a corporeal creature, but to use it against an incorporeal creature, you must open the flask and pour the holy water out onto the target. Thus, you can douse an incorporeal creature with holy water only if you are adjacent to it. Doing so is a ranged touch attack that does not provoke attacks of opportunity.</para><para>A direct hit by a flask of holy water deals 2d4 points of damage to an undead creature or an evil outsider. Each such creature within 5 feet of the point where the flask hits takes 1 point of damage from the splash.</para><para>Temples to good deities sell holy water at cost (making no profit).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Smokestick" origname="Smokestick" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Smokestick" docbookid="Equipment133" refname="Smokestick" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,item,servic,smokestick,special,substanc"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Smokestick"><b>Smokestick:</b> This alchemically treated wooden stick instantly creates thick, opaque smoke when ignited. The smoke fills a 10- foot cube (treat the effect as a <i>fog cloud</i> spell, except that a moderate or stronger wind dissipates the smoke in 1 round). The stick is consumed after 1 round, and the smoke dissipates naturally.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sunrod" origname="Sunrod" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Sunrod" docbookid="Equipment134" refname="Sunrod" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc,sunrod"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sunrod"><b>Sunrod:</b> This 1-foot-long, gold-tipped, iron rod glows brightly when struck. It clearly illuminates a 30-foot radius and provides shadowy illumination in a 60-foot radius. It glows for 6 hours, after which the gold tip is burned out and worthless.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Tanglefoot Bag" origname="Tanglefoot Bag" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Tanglefoot_Bag" docbookid="Equipment135" refname="Tanglefoot Bag" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="bag,equip,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc,tanglefoot"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Tanglefoot Bag"><b>Tanglefoot Bag:</b> When you throw a tanglefoot bag at a creature (as a ranged touch attack with a range increment of 10 feet), the bag comes apart and the goo bursts out, entangling the target and then becoming tough and resilient upon exposure to air. An entangled creature takes a -2 penalty on attack rolls and a -4 penalty to Dexterity and must make a DC 15 Reflex save or be glued to the floor, unable to move. Even on a successful save, it can move only at half speed. Huge or larger creatures are unaffected by a tanglefoot bag. A flying creature is not stuck to the floor, but it must make a DC 15 Reflex save or be unable to fly (assuming it uses its wings to fly) and fall to the ground. A tanglefoot bag does not function underwater.</para><para>A creature that is glued to the floor (or unable to fly) can break free by making a DC 17 Strength check or by dealing 15 points of damage to the goo with a slashing weapon. A creature trying to scrape goo off itself, or another creature assisting, does not need to make an attack roll; hitting the goo is automatic, after which the creature that hit makes a damage roll to see how much of the goo was scraped off. Once free, the creature can move (including flying) at half speed. A character capable of spellcasting who is bound by the goo must make a DC 15 Concentration check to cast a spell. The goo becomes brittle and fragile after 2d4 rounds, cracking apart and losing its effectiveness. An application of <i>universal solvent</i> to a stuck creature dissolves the alchemical goo immediately.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Thunderstone" origname="Thunderstone" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Thunderstone" docbookid="Equipment136" refname="Thunderstone" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc,thunderston"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Thunderstone"><b>Thunderstone:</b> You can throw this stone as a ranged attack with a range increment of 20 feet. When it strikes a hard surface (or is struck hard), it creates a deafening bang that is treated as a sonic attack. Each creature within a 10-foot-radius spread must make a DC 15 Fortitude save or be deafened for 1 hour. A deafened creature, in addition to the obvious effects, takes a -4 penalty on initiative and has a 20% chance to miscast and lose any spell with a verbal component that it tries to cast.</para><para>Since you don't need to hit a specific target, you can simply aim at a particular 5-foot square. Treat the target square as AC 5.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Tindertwig" origname="Tindertwig" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Special_Substances_and_Items_Tindertwig" docbookid="Equipment137" refname="Tindertwig" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,item,servic,special,substanc,tindertwig"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Tindertwig"><b>Tindertwig:</b> The alchemical substance on the end of this small, wooden stick ignites when struck against a rough surface. Creating a flame with a tindertwig is much faster than creating a flame with flint and steel (or a magnifying glass) and tinder. Lighting a torch with a tindertwig is a standard action (rather than a full-round action), and lighting any other fire with one is at least a standard action.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Tools and Skill Kits" origname="Tools and Skill Kits" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits" docbookid="Equipment138" refname="Tools and Skill Kits" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,kit,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Tools and Skill Kits" style="heading 3">Tools and Skill Kits</para><topic level="8" name="Alchemist's Lab" origname="Alchemist's Lab" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Alchemist_s_Lab" docbookid="Equipment139" refname="Alchemist's Lab" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="alchemist,equip,gear,good,kit,lab,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Alchemist's Lab"><b>Alchemist's Lab:</b> An alchemist's lab always has the perfect tool for making alchemical items, so it provides a +2 circumstance bonus on Craft (alchemy) checks. It has no bearing on the costs related to the Craft (alchemy) skill. Without this lab, a character with the Craft (alchemy) skill is assumed to have enough tools to use the skill but not enough to get the +2 bonus that the lab provides.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Artisan's Tools" origname="Artisan's Tools" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Artisan_s_Tools" docbookid="Equipment140" refname="Artisan's Tools" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="artisan,equip,gear,good,kit,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Artisan's Tools"><b>Artisan's Tools:</b> These special tools include the items needed to pursue any craft. Without them, you have to use improvised tools (-2 penalty on Craft checks), if you can do the job at all.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Artisan's Tools, Masterwork" origname="Artisan's Tools, Masterwork" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Artisan_s_Tools_Masterwork" docbookid="Equipment141" refname="Artisan's Tools, Masterwork" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="artisan,equip,gear,good,kit,masterwork,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Artisan's Tools, Masterwork"><b>Artisan's Tools, Masterwork:</b> These tools serve the same purpose as artisan's tools (above), but masterwork artisan's tools are the perfect tools for the job, so you get a +2 circumstance bonus on Craft checks made with them.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Climber's Kit" origname="Climber's Kit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Climber_s_Kit" docbookid="Equipment142" refname="Climber's Kit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="climber,equip,gear,good,kit,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Climber's Kit"><b>Climber's Kit:</b> This is the perfect tool for climbing and gives you a +2 circumstance bonus on Climb checks.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Disguise Kit" origname="Disguise Kit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Disguise_Kit" docbookid="Equipment143" refname="Disguise Kit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="disguis,equip,gear,good,kit,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Disguise Kit"><b>Disguise Kit:</b> The kit is the perfect tool for disguise and provides a +2 circumstance bonus on Disguise checks. A disguise kit is exhausted after ten uses.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Healer's Kit" origname="Healer's Kit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Healer_s_Kit" docbookid="Equipment144" refname="Healer's Kit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,healer,kit,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Healer's Kit"><b>Healer's Kit:</b> It is the perfect tool for healing and provides a +2 circumstance bonus on Heal checks. A healer's kit is exhausted after ten uses.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Holy Symbol, Silver or Wooden" origname="Holy Symbol, Silver or Wooden" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Holy_Symbol_Silver_or_Wooden" docbookid="Equipment145" refname="Holy Symbol, Silver or Wooden" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,holi,kit,servic,silver,skill,symbol,tool,wooden"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Holy Symbol, Silver or Wooden"><b>Holy Symbol, Silver or Wooden:</b> A holy symbol focuses positive energy. A cleric or paladin uses it as the focus for his spells and as a tool for turning undead. Each religion has its own holy symbol.</para><para><i>Unholy Symbols:</i> An unholy symbol is like a holy symbol except that it focuses negative energy and is used by evil clerics (or by neutral clerics who want to cast evil spells or command undead).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Magnifying Glass" origname="Magnifying Glass" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Magnifying_Glass" docbookid="Equipment146" refname="Magnifying Glass" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,glass,good,kit,magnifi,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Magnifying Glass"><b>Magnifying Glass:</b> This simple lens allows a closer look at small objects. It is also useful as a substitute for flint and steel when starting fires. Lighting a fire with a magnifying glass requires light as bright as sunlight to focus, tinder to ignite, and at least a full-round action. A magnifying glass grants a +2 circumstance bonus on Appraise checks involving any item that is small or highly detailed.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Musical Instrument, Common or Masterwork" origname="Musical Instrument, Common or Masterwork" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Musical_Instrument_Common_or_Masterwork" docbookid="Equipment147" refname="Musical Instrument, Common or Masterwork" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="common,equip,gear,good,instrum,kit,masterwork,music,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Musical Instrument, Common or Masterwork"><b>Musical Instrument, Common or Masterwork:</b> A masterwork instrument grants a +2 circumstance bonus on Perform checks involving its use.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Scale, Merchant's" origname="Scale, Merchant's" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Scale_Merchant_s" docbookid="Equipment148" refname="Scale, Merchant's" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,kit,merchant,scale,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Scale, Merchant's"><b>Scale, Merchant's:</b> A scale grants a +2 circumstance bonus on Appraise checks involving items that are valued by weight, including anything made of precious metals.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Spell Component Pouch" origname="Spell Component Pouch" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Spell_Component_Pouch" docbookid="Equipment149" refname="Spell Component Pouch" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="compon,equip,gear,good,kit,pouch,servic,skill,spell,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spell Component Pouch"><b>Spell Component Pouch:</b> A spellcaster with a spell component pouch is assumed to have all the material components and focuses needed for spellcasting, except for those components that have a specific cost, divine focuses, and focuses that wouldn't fit in a pouch.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Spellbook, Wizard's" origname="Spellbook, Wizard's (Blank)" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Spellbook_Wizard_s" docbookid="Equipment150" refname="Spellbook, Wizard's" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,kit,servic,skill,spellbook,tool,wizard"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spellbook, Wizard's"><b>Spellbook, Wizard's (Blank):</b> A spellbook has 100 pages of parchment, and each spell takes up one page per spell level (one page each for 0-level spells).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Thieves' Tools" origname="Thieves' Tools" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Thieves_Tools" docbookid="Equipment151" refname="Thieves' Tools" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,kit,servic,skill,thiev,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Thieves' Tools"><b>Thieves' Tools:</b> This kit contains the tools you need to use the Disable Device and Open Lock skills. Without these tools, you must improvise tools, and you take a -2 circumstance penalty on Disable Device and Open Locks checks.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Thieves' Tools, Masterwork" origname="Thieves' Tools, Masterwork" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Thieves_Tools_Masterwork" docbookid="Equipment152" refname="Thieves' Tools, Masterwork" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,kit,masterwork,servic,skill,thiev,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Thieves' Tools, Masterwork"><b>Thieves' Tools, Masterwork:</b> This kit contains extra tools and tools of better make, which grant a +2 circumstance bonus on Disable Device and Open Lock checks.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Tool, Masterwork" origname="Tool, Masterwork" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Tool_Masterwork" docbookid="Equipment153" refname="Tool, Masterwork" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,kit,masterwork,servic,skill,tool"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Tool, Masterwork"><b>Tool, Masterwork:</b> This well-made item is the perfect tool for the job. It grants a +2 circumstance bonus on a related skill check (if any). Bonuses provided by multiple masterwork items used toward the same skill check do not stack.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Water Clock" origname="Water Clock" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Tools_and_Skill_Kits_Water_Clock" docbookid="Equipment154" refname="Water Clock" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="clock,equip,gear,good,kit,servic,skill,tool,water"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Water Clock"><b>Water Clock:</b> This large, bulky contrivance gives the time accurate to within half an hour per day since it was last set. It requires a source of water, and it must be kept still because it marks time by the regulated flow of droplets of water.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Clothing" origname="Clothing" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing" docbookid="Equipment155" refname="Clothing" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,gear,good,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Clothing" style="heading 3">Clothing</para><topic level="8" name="Artisan's Outfit" origname="Artisan's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Artisan_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment156" refname="Artisan's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="artisan,cloth,equip,gear,good,outfit,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Artisan's Outfit"><b>Artisan's Outfit:</b> This outfit includes a shirt with buttons, a skirt or pants with a drawstring, shoes, and perhaps a cap or hat. It may also include a belt or a leather or cloth apron for carrying tools.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Cleric's Vestments" origname="Cleric's Vestments" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Cleric_s_Vestments" docbookid="Equipment157" refname="Cleric's Vestments" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cleric,cloth,equip,gear,good,servic,vestment"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Cleric's Vestments"><b>Cleric's Vestments:</b> These ecclesiastical clothes are for performing priestly functions, not for adventuring.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Cold Weather Outfit" origname="Cold Weather Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Cold_Weather_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment158" refname="Cold Weather Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,cold,equip,gear,good,outfit,servic,weather"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Cold Weather Outfit"><b>Cold Weather Outfit:</b> A cold weather outfit includes a wool coat, linen shirt, wool cap, heavy cloak, thick pants or skirt, and boots. This outfit grants a +5 circumstance bonus on Fortitude saving throws against exposure to cold weather.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Courtier's Outfit" origname="Courtier's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Courtier_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment159" refname="Courtier's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,courtier,equip,gear,good,outfit,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Courtier's Outfit"><b>Courtier's Outfit:</b> This outfit includes fancy, tailored clothes in whatever fashion happens to be the current style in the courts of the nobles. Anyone trying to influence nobles or courtiers while wearing street dress will have a hard time of it (-2 penalty on Charisma-based skill checks to influence such individuals). If you wear this outfit without jewelry (costing an additional 50 gp), you look like an out-of-place commoner.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Entertainer's Outfit" origname="Entertainer's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Entertainer_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment160" refname="Entertainer's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,entertain,equip,gear,good,outfit,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Entertainer's Outfit"><b>Entertainer's Outfit:</b> This set of flashy, perhaps even gaudy, clothes is for entertaining. While the outfit looks whimsical, its practical design lets you tumble, dance, walk a tightrope, or just run (if the audience turns ugly).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Explorer's Outfit" origname="Explorer's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Explorer_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment161" refname="Explorer's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,explor,gear,good,outfit,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Explorer's Outfit"><b>Explorer's Outfit:</b> This is a full set of clothes for someone who never knows what to expect. It includes sturdy boots, leather breeches or a skirt, a belt, a shirt (perhaps with a vest or jacket), gloves, and a cloak. Rather than a leather skirt, a leather overtunic may be worn over a cloth skirt. The clothes have plenty of pockets (especially the cloak). The outfit also includes any extra items you might need, such as a scarf or a wide-brimmed hat.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Monk's Outfit" origname="Monk's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Monk_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment162" refname="Monk's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,gear,good,monk,outfit,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Monk's Outfit"><b>Monk's Outfit:</b> This simple outfit includes sandals, loose breeches, and a loose shirt, and is all bound together with sashes. The outfit is designed to give you maximum mobility, and it's made of high-quality fabric. You can hide small weapons in pockets hidden in the folds, and the sashes are strong enough to serve as short ropes.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Noble's Outfit" origname="Noble's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Noble_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment163" refname="Noble's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,gear,good,nobl,outfit,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Noble's Outfit"><b>Noble's Outfit:</b> This set of clothes is designed specifically to be expensive and to show it. Precious metals and gems are worked into the clothing. To fit into the noble crowd, every would-be noble also needs a signet ring (see Adventuring Gear, above) and jewelry (worth at least 100 gp).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Peasant's Outfit" origname="Peasant's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Peasant_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment164" refname="Peasant's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,gear,good,outfit,peasant,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Peasant's Outfit"><b>Peasant's Outfit:</b> This set of clothes consists of a loose shirt and baggy breeches, or a loose shirt and skirt or overdress. Cloth wrappings are used for shoes.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Royal Outfit" origname="Royal Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Royal_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment165" refname="Royal Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,gear,good,outfit,royal,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Royal Outfit"><b>Royal Outfit:</b> This is just the clothing, not the royal scepter, crown, ring, and other accoutrements. Royal clothes are ostentatious, with gems, gold, silk, and fur in abundance.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Scholar's Outfit" origname="Scholar's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Scholar_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment166" refname="Scholar's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,gear,good,outfit,scholar,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Scholar's Outfit"><b>Scholar's Outfit:</b> Perfect for a scholar, this outfit includes a robe, a belt, a cap, soft shoes, and possibly a cloak.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Traveler's Outfit" origname="Traveler's Outfit" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Clothing_Traveler_s_Outfit" docbookid="Equipment167" refname="Traveler's Outfit" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cloth,equip,gear,good,outfit,servic,travel"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Traveler's Outfit"><b>Traveler's Outfit:</b> This set of clothes consists of boots, a wool skirt or breeches, a sturdy belt, a shirt (perhaps with a vest or jacket), and an ample cloak with a hood.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Food, Drink, and Lodging" origname="Food, Drink, and Lodging" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Food_Drink_and_Lodging" docbookid="Equipment168" refname="Food, Drink, and Lodging" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="drink,equip,food,gear,good,lodg,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Food, Drink, and Lodging" style="heading 3">Food, Drink, and Lodging</para><topic level="8" name="Inn" origname="Inn" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Food_Drink_and_Lodging_Inn" docbookid="Equipment169" refname="Inn" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="drink,equip,food,gear,good,inn,lodg,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Inn"><b>Inn:</b> Poor accommodations at an inn amount to a place on the floor near the hearth. Common accommodations consist of a place on a raised, heated floor, the use of a blanket and a pillow. Good accommodations consist of a small, private room with one bed, some amenities, and a covered chamber pot in the corner.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Meals" origname="Meals" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Food_Drink_and_Lodging_Meals" docbookid="Equipment170" refname="Meals" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="drink,equip,food,gear,good,lodg,meal,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Meals"><b>Meals:</b> Poor meals might be composed of bread, baked turnips, onions, and water. Common meals might consist of bread, chicken stew, carrots, and watered-down ale or wine. Good meals might be composed of bread and pastries, beef, peas, and ale or wine.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Mounts and Related Gear" origname="Mounts and Related Gear" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear" docbookid="Equipment171" refname="Mounts and Related Gear" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,mount,relat,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Mounts and Related Gear" style="heading 3">Mounts and Related Gear</para><topic level="8" name="Barding, Medium Creature and Large Creature" origname="Barding, Medium Creature and Large Creature" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Barding_Medium_Creature_and_Large_Creature" docbookid="Equipment172" refname="Barding, Medium Creature and Large Creature" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="bard,creatur,equip,gear,good,larg,medium,mount,relat,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Barding, Medium Creature and Large Creature"><b>Barding, Medium Creature and Large Creature:</b> Barding is a type of armor that covers the head, neck, chest, body, and possibly legs of a horse or other mount. Barding made of medium or heavy armor provides better protection than light barding, but at the expense of speed. Barding can be made of any of the armor types found on Table: Armor and Shields.</para><para>Armor for a horse (a Large nonhumanoid creature) costs four times as much as armor for a human (a Medium humanoid creature) and also weighs twice as much as the armor found on Table: Armor and Shields (see Armor for Unusual Creatures). If the barding is for a pony or other Medium mount, the cost is only double, and the weight is the same as for Medium armor worn by a humanoid. Medium or heavy barding slows a mount that wears it, as shown on the table below.</para><para/><table>
<row/>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell><para><b>---- Base Speed -----</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para><b>Barding</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>(40 ft.)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>(50 ft.)</b></para></cell>
<cell><para><b>(60 ft.)</b></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Medium</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>35 ft.</para></cell>
<cell><para>40 ft.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row>
<cell><para>Heavy</para></cell>
<cell><para>30 ft.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>35 ft.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell><para>40 ft.<sup><b>1</b></sup></para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
<row/>
<row>
<cell><para>1 A mount wearing heavy armor moves at only triple its normal speed when running instead of quadruple.</para></cell>
<cell/>
</row>
</table><para/><para>Flying mounts can't fly in medium or heavy barding.</para><para>Removing and fitting barding takes five times as long as the figures given on Table: Donning Armor. A barded animal cannot be used to carry any load other than the rider and normal saddlebags.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Dog, Riding" origname="Dog, Riding" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Dog_Riding" docbookid="Equipment173" refname="Dog, Riding" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="dog,equip,gear,good,mount,relat,ride,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Dog, Riding"><b>Dog, Riding:</b> This Medium dog is specially trained to carry a Small humanoid rider. It is brave in combat like a warhorse. You take no damage when you fall from a riding dog.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Donkey or Mule" origname="Donkey or Mule" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Donkey_or_Mule" docbookid="Equipment174" refname="Donkey or Mule" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="donkei,equip,gear,good,mount,mule,relat,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Donkey or Mule"><b>Donkey or Mule:</b> Donkeys and mules are stolid in the face of danger, hardy, surefooted, and capable of carrying heavy loads over vast distances. Unlike a horse, a donkey or a mule is willing (though not eager) to enter dungeons and other strange or threatening places.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Feed" origname="Feed" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Feed" docbookid="Equipment175" refname="Feed" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,fe,gear,good,mount,relat,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Feed"><b>Feed:</b> Horses, donkeys, mules, and ponies can graze to sustain themselves, but providing feed for them is much better. If you have a riding dog, you have to feed it at least some meat.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Horse" origname="Horse" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Horse" docbookid="Equipment176" refname="Horse" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,hors,mount,relat,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Horse"><b>Horse:</b> A horse (other than a pony) is suitable as a mount for a human, dwarf, elf, half-elf, or half-orc. A pony is smaller than a horse and is a suitable mount for a gnome or halfling.</para><para>Warhorses and warponies can be ridden easily into combat. Light horses, ponies, and heavy horses are hard to control in combat.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Saddle, Exotic" origname="Saddle, Exotic" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Saddle_Exotic" docbookid="Equipment177" refname="Saddle, Exotic" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,exot,gear,good,mount,relat,saddl,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Saddle, Exotic"><b>Saddle, Exotic:</b> An exotic saddle is like a normal saddle of the same sort except that it is designed for an unusual mount. Exotic saddles come in military, pack, and riding styles.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Saddle, Military" origname="Saddle, Military" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Saddle_Military" docbookid="Equipment178" refname="Saddle, Military" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,militari,mount,relat,saddl,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Saddle, Military"><b>Saddle, Military:</b> A military saddle braces the rider, providing a +2 circumstance bonus on Ride checks related to staying in the saddle. If you're knocked unconscious while in a military saddle, you have a 75% chance to stay in the saddle (compared to 50% for a riding saddle).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Saddle, Pack" origname="Saddle, Pack" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Saddle_Pack" docbookid="Equipment179" refname="Saddle, Pack" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,mount,pack,relat,saddl,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Saddle, Pack"><b>Saddle, Pack:</b> A pack saddle holds gear and supplies, but not a rider. It holds as much gear as the mount can carry.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Saddle, Riding" origname="Saddle, Riding" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Mounts_and_Related_Gear_Saddle_Riding" docbookid="Equipment180" refname="Saddle, Riding" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,mount,relat,ride,saddl,servic"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Saddle, Riding"><b>Saddle, Riding:</b> The standard riding saddle supports a rider.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Transport" origname="Transport" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport" docbookid="Equipment181" refname="Transport" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,servic,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Transport" style="heading 3">Transport</para><topic level="5" name="Carriage" origname="Carriage" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage" docbookid="Equipment182" refname="Carriage" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,servic,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Carriage"><b>Carriage</b>: This four-wheeled vehicle can transport as many as four people within an enclosed cab, plus two drivers. In general, two horses (or other beasts of burden) draw it. A carriage comes with the harness needed to pull it.</para><topic level="8" name="Cart" origname="Cart" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Cart" docbookid="Equipment183" refname="Cart" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,cart,equip,gear,good,servic,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Cart"><b>Cart:</b> This two-wheeled vehicle can be drawn by a single horse (or other beast of burden). It comes with a harness.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Galley" origname="Galley" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Galley" docbookid="Equipment184" refname="Galley" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gallei,gear,good,servic,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Galley"><b>Galley:</b> This three-masted ship has seventy oars on either side and requires a total crew of 200. A galley is 130 feet long and 20 feet wide, and it can carry 150 tons of cargo or 250 soldiers. For 8,000 gp more, it can be fitted with a ram and castles with firing platforms fore, aft, and amidships. This ship cannot make sea voyages and sticks to the coast. It moves about 4 miles per hour when being rowed or under sail.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Keelboat" origname="Keelboat" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Keelboat" docbookid="Equipment185" refname="Keelboat" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,keelboat,servic,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Keelboat"><b>Keelboat:</b> This 50- to 75-foot-long ship is 15 to 20 feet wide and has a few oars to supplement its single mast with a square sail. It has a crew of eight to fifteen and can carry 40 to 50 tons of cargo or 100 soldiers. It can make sea voyages, as well as sail down rivers (thanks to its flat bottom). It moves about 1 mile per hour.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Longship" origname="Longship" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Longship" docbookid="Equipment186" refname="Longship" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,longship,servic,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Longship"><b>Longship:</b> This 75-foot-long ship with forty oars requires a total crew of 50. It has a single mast and a square sail, and it can carry 50 tons of cargo or 120 soldiers. A longship can make sea voyages. It moves about 3 miles per hour when being rowed or under sail.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Rowboat" origname="Rowboat" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Rowboat" docbookid="Equipment187" refname="Rowboat" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,rowboat,servic,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Rowboat"><b>Rowboat:</b> This 8- to 12-foot-long boat holds two or three Medium passengers. It moves about 1-1/2 miles per hour.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sailing Ship" origname="Sailing Ship" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Sailing_Ship" docbookid="Equipment188" refname="Sailing Ship" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,sail,servic,ship,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sailing Ship"><b>Sailing Ship:</b> This larger, seaworthy ship is 75 to 90 feet long and 20 feet wide and has a crew of 20. It can carry 150 tons of cargo. It has square sails on its two masts and can make sea voyages. It moves about 2 miles per hour.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Sled" origname="Sled" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Sled" docbookid="Equipment189" refname="Sled" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,servic,sled,transport"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Sled"><b>Sled:</b> This is a wagon on runners for moving through snow and over ice. In general, two horses (or other beasts of burden) draw it. A sled comes with the harness needed to pull it.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Wagon" origname="Wagon" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Wagon" docbookid="Equipment190" refname="Wagon" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,servic,transport,wagon"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Wagon"><b>Wagon:</b> This is a four-wheeled, open vehicle for transporting heavy loads. In general, two horses (or other beasts of burden) draw it. A wagon comes with the harness needed to pull it.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Warship" origname="Warship" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Transport_Carriage_Warship" docbookid="Equipment191" refname="Warship" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="carriag,equip,gear,good,servic,transport,warship"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Warship"><b>Warship:</b> This 100-foot-long ship has a single mast, although oars can also propel it. It has a crew of 60 to 80 rowers. This ship can carry 160 soldiers, but not for long distances, since there isn't room for supplies to support that many people. The warship cannot make sea voyages and sticks to the coast. It is not used for cargo. It moves about 2-1/2 miles per hour when being rowed or under sail.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic>
</topic><topic level="3" name="Spellcasting and Services" origname="Spellcasting and Services" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services" docbookid="Equipment192" refname="Spellcasting and Services" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,servic,spellcast"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spellcasting and Services" style="heading 3">Spellcasting and Services</para><para>Sometimes the best solution for a problem is to hire someone else to take care of it.</para><topic level="8" name="Coach Cab" origname="Coach Cab" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services_Coach_Cab" docbookid="Equipment193" refname="Coach Cab" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="cab,coach,equip,gear,good,servic,spellcast"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Coach Cab"><b>Coach Cab:</b> The price given is for a ride in a coach that transports people (and light cargo) between towns. For a ride in a cab that transports passengers within a city, 1 copper piece usually takes you anywhere you need to go.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Hireling, Trained" origname="Hireling, Trained" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services_Hireling_Trained" docbookid="Equipment194" refname="Hireling, Trained" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,hirel,servic,spellcast,train"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Hireling, Trained"><b>Hireling, Trained:</b> The amount given is the typical daily wage for mercenary warriors, masons, craftsmen, scribes, teamsters, and other trained hirelings. This value represents a minimum wage; many such hirelings require significantly higher pay.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Hireling, Untrained" origname="Hireling, Untrained" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services_Hireling_Untrained" docbookid="Equipment195" refname="Hireling, Untrained" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,hirel,servic,spellcast,untrain"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Hireling, Untrained"><b>Hireling, Untrained:</b> The amount shown is the typical daily wage for laborers, porters, cooks, maids, and other menial workers.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Messenger" origname="Messenger" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services_Messenger" docbookid="Equipment196" refname="Messenger" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,messeng,servic,spellcast"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Messenger"><b>Messenger:</b> This entry includes horse-riding messengers and runners. Those willing to carry a message to a place they were going anyway may ask for only half the indicated amount.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Road or Gate Toll" origname="Road or Gate Toll" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services_Road_or_Gate_Toll" docbookid="Equipment197" refname="Road or Gate Toll" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gate,gear,good,road,servic,spellcast,toll"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Road or Gate Toll"><b>Road or Gate Toll:</b> A toll is sometimes charged to cross a well-trodden, well-kept, and well-guarded road to pay for patrols on it and for its upkeep. Occasionally, a large walled city charges a toll to enter or exit (or sometimes just to enter).</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Ship's Passage" origname="Ship's Passage" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services_Ship_s_Passage" docbookid="Equipment198" refname="Ship's Passage" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,passag,servic,ship,spellcast"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Ship's Passage"><b>Ship's Passage:</b> Most ships do not specialize in passengers, but many have the capability to take a few along when transporting cargo. Double the given cost for creatures larger than Medium or creatures that are otherwise difficult to bring aboard a ship.</para>
</topic><topic level="8" name="Spell" origname="Spell" linkname="Equipment_and_Gear_Equipment_Goods_and_Services_Spellcasting_and_Services_Spell" docbookid="Equipment199" refname="Spell" reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refaltname="" keywords="equip,gear,good,servic,spell,spellcast"><para reftype="equipment" refcase="no" refname="Spell"><b>Spell:</b> The indicated amount is how much it costs to get a spellcaster to cast a spell for you. This cost assumes that you can go to the spellcaster and have the spell cast at his or her convenience (generally at least 24 hours later, so that the spellcaster has time to prepare the spell in question). If you want to bring the spellcaster somewhere to cast a spell you need to negotiate with him or her, and the default answer is no.</para><para>The cost given is for a spell with no cost for a material component or focus component and no XP cost. If the spell includes a material component, add the cost of that component to the cost of the spell.</para><para>If the spell has a focus component (other than a divine focus), add 1/10 the cost of that focus to the cost of the spell. If the spell has an XP cost, add 5 gp per XP lost.</para><para>Furthermore, if a spell has dangerous consequences, the spellcaster will certainly require proof that you can and will pay for dealing with any such consequences (that is, assuming that the spellcaster even agrees to cast such a spell, which isn't certain). In the case of spells that transport the caster and characters over a distance, you will likely have to pay for two castings of the spell, even if you aren't returning with the caster.</para><para>In addition, not every town or village has a spellcaster of sufficient level to cast any spell. In general, you must travel to a small town (or larger settlement) to be reasonably assured of finding a spellcaster capable of casting 1st-level spells, a large town for 2nd-level spells, a small city for 3rd- or 4th-level spells, a large city for 5th- or 6th-level spells, and a metropolis for 7th- or 8th-level spells. Even a metropolis isn't guaranteed to have a local spellcaster able to cast 9th-level spells.</para><para/>
</topic>
</topic>
</topic>
</topic>
</topic></document>
